洛奇
1975年11月25日-费城
加油... 打他! 打他!
Come on... hit him! Hit him!
你像在跳舞  要给他一点颜色看
You're waltzing. Give this sucker some action.
你打得有气无力
You're fighting like a bum.
要忠告吗?
You want some advice?
水
Water.
有冰冻啤酒
Cold beer here. Get your beer.
加油!
Come on!
我应该赌三个回合以内玩完吗?
Rocky, should I bet the fight don't go three rounds?
-你有信心?  -绝对有
-You feel strong?  -Absolutely.
你要好的忠告吗?
You want some good advice?
-护齿胶  -张开嘴...
-Mouthpiece. -Move into your...
加油  上!
Come on, let's go!
给他点空间!
Give him room!
举起手来!
Hold your hands up!
好了  好了
All right. All right.
接着是一场六回合比赛 本地轻量级拳手
Next, a six-rounder between local lightweights
杰博斯对约拿逊
Kid Brooks and Sugar Johnson.
打得好  冠军拳手
Good going, champ!
-嘿  -嘿  什么?
-Hey. -Hey, what?
-有烟吗?  -有  这支给你
-You got a smoke? -Yeah, you could have this one.
你是废柴
You're a bum.
你是废柴...知道吗?  你是废物!
You're a bum... you know that? You're a bum!
意大利牡马
算你今晚好运
You really got lucky tonight.
史派德 这是输了的酬劳40元  扣除15元储物柜和助手费
Spider, here's your share. $40.00, less $15 locker and corner man,
5元浴室和毛巾  7%税
$5 shower and towel, 7% tax.
总数是17元2角
Comes to $17.20
史派德  你今晚打得不错
You fought a good fight, Spider.
巴尔博亚  胜出者分得
Balboa, you get winner's share.
65元  扣除15元储物柜和助手费
$65 less $15 locker and corner end,
5元浴室和毛巾  加7%税
$5 shower and towel and 7% tax,
总数是40元5角半
comes to $40.55
我何时再出赛?
When do I fight again?
可能两星期后  到时打电话给我
Maybe two weeks. Give me a call.
医生20分钟内应该到
The doctor should be in in about 20 minutes.
嘿  狗仔
Hey, boy.
专业拳击
你们一年好过一年  知道吗?
You guys are gettin' better every year, you know that?
嘿  你老爹今晚打得不错
Hey, your old man did pretty good tonight.
你干吗没去看?  你应该去看我比赛
Why weren't you there, huh? You should've seen me.
肚子饿吗?
You guys hungry? Huh?
来
Here you go.
吃吧
你想看老友莫比·狄克吗?
You wanna see your friend Moby Dick, huh?
莫比·狄克  你好吗?  今天挂念我吗?
How're you doin', Moby Dick? You missed me today or what? Huh?
在这里了  打招呼吧
Here you go. Say hi.
如果你们懂唱歌跳舞
You know, if you guys could sing or dance,
我就不用这样  你知道的
I wouldn't be doin' this, you know.
上次买的龟粮
And, uh, last turtle food I got here.
那个...我上次买的龟粮
That's, uh... last turtle food I got here.
这龟粮里有很多乌蝇...蛾多过乌蝇
It had more flies in it... more moths and flies.
乌蝇多些...蛾多些...谁他妈在乎?
More flies... more moths... who the hell cares?
今早好吗?   精神好吗?
How you feelin' this morning, huh? Full of life?
很好
Fine.
你好吗  杀手?  这星期的龟粮如何?
Hey, how you doin', killer? How's the turtle food this week?
很好
Fine.
我心情很不好呢
Me, I'm kind of aggravated, you know?
噢  真抱歉
Oh, I'm sorry.
不是你的错  你不想知原因吗?
Not your fault. I'm just kind of aggravated. Wanna hear about it?
总之有人不想听
I'll tell you somebody who don't wanna hear about it.
-歌莉亚  你好吗?  -好
-How you doin', Gloria?  -Yeah.
我上次在这里买的龟粮 里面蛾多过乌蝇
The last turtle food I got had more moths in it than flies,you know,Adrian?
蛾会卡在龟的喉咙里  就在这里
And these moths get caught in the turtle's throat, right about here,
它们就会咳嗽  我还得替它们拍龟壳
and they cough, and I gotta smack 'em on the back of the shell.
你认为它们会怎样?  会怎样?
And what do you think they get, huh? And they get what?
说啊
Come on.
得脑震荡
Shell shock.
你一早就来说差劲的笑话
You're startin' with bad jokes early, huh?
要发明笑话  有时也不容易
Well, no, it's just inventin' jokes ain't so easy sometimes.
别讲笑话了  行不?
No joke, huh?
嘿  我老友今天怎么样?  喂  毕寇斯
Hey, how's my buddy doin' today? Yo, Butkus!
-我还没时间去看他  -喂  毕寇斯
-I ain't had time to check on him. -Yo, Butkus!
嘿  亲我一下
Hey, gimme a kiss.
亲我一下  毕寇斯
Gimme a kiss, Butkus.
艾莉  你下去清洗一下猫笼
Adrian, I want you to go downstairs and clean all the cat cages.
很脏呢
They're a mess.
那些龟粮你要付钱的  傻佬
You gotta pay for that turtle food, rockhead.
我是贼...你知道的  歌莉亚
Hey, crime don't pay... you know that, Gloria. You know that.
-喂  洛奇  你老板好吗?  -很好
-Yo, Rock, how's your boss?  -Real good.
-洛奇  有再打拳吗?  -是的  是的
-Hey, Rock, you fightin' again? -Yeah, yeah.
我们很快会赚大钱?
Hey, we'll make some money real soon, huh?
对  赚一百万
Yeah, a million dollars.
喂  你要去哪里?
Hey, you. Where you goin'?
你去哪里?  要跑去哪里?
Where you goin', huh? Where you runnin'?
跑去哪里?
Where you runnin'?
-喂! 不要打脸!  -闭嘴!
-Hey! Don't hit the face! -Shut up!
-不要打脸!  -加索先生要那200元
-Not the face!  -Mr. Gazzo wants the 200 now.
我没钱...向上帝发誓!
I'm broke... honest to God!
加索先生说  如果我收不到200元 就打断你手指  明白吗
Mr. Gazzo says I should get the 200 or break your thumb, you understand?
-求你!  不要...  -你叫什么名字?
-Please! Please... -What's your name again?
-鲍伯  -鲍伯  听着  鲍伯
-Bob. -Bob. Listen, Bob. Listen, Bob!
有借有还  明白吗?
You wanna dance, you gotta pay the band, understand?
你要借钱  就自然要还
You wanna borrow, you gotta pay the man.
我不会同情你  知道吗?
Hey, I ain't emotionally involved, Bob, you understand?
把钱给我
Give me some money.
Give me some money. Come on.
这里只有130元
There's 130 here.
就那么多  我没钱了
That's it. That's it. I'm broke.
鲍伯  还差70元
Hey, Bob. Hey, hey. You're still $70 light.
你不用打断我手指  我的外套拿去
You don't have to break nothing. Here, take my coat.
值五六十元的
It's worth 50, $60.
不要外套
Here. Take the coat. Take the coat!
-拿走...  -你应该未雨绸缪
-Just...  -No, you should've planned ahead.
知道吗?  你应该未雨绸缪
You know that? You should've planned ahead.
我们可以假装 我的手被你打断了
We'll fake it. I'll tape up the hand like you broke the thumb.
应该未雨绸缪
You should've planned ahead.
加索不用知道!  加索不会知道一切
Gazzo don't have to know! He won't be wise to nothin'!
加索不会知道一切  把外套拿去
Gazzo won't be wise to nothin'. Keep the coat!
拿去...
Keep the...
加索先生 他只有130元 但我估他下周可还清
He only had 130, but I think he's good for the rest next week, Mr.Gazzo.
好的  洛奇  暂时放过鲍伯吧
Sure, Rocky. Bob's good for it.
今天就那么多
That's it for today. Here.
明天去度里奥处收帐
Tomorrow collect from Del Rio.
他迟了三星期  我不喜欢
He's late three weeks and I don't like it.
明天  三星期  度里奥?
Tomorrow, three weeks, Del Rio?
好  知道了    度里奥怎样写?
All right, I got it. Del Rio...how do you spell Del Rio?
-昨晚表现如何?  -非常好
-How'd you do last night?  -I did real good.
-嘿  -什么事?
-Hey!  -What?
-你有记车牌吗?  -什么车牌?
-Did you get the license number?  -Of what?
那架辗过你脸的货车车牌
The truck that run over your face.
放松点  老兄  在这里停车
Relax, Buddy. All right, pull it over here.
我想下车跟洛奇说几句
I wanna let Rocky out, then I'm gonna talk to him for a few seconds.
你干吗没打断他的手指?
How come you didn't break this guy's thumb like I told you?
-你怎知我没有?  -你以为我不会收到报告?
-How do you know I didn't... -You don't think I hear things?
我今早不是给了你指示吗?
Did I give you a job this morning or I didn't, huh?
-是  -那你干吗不打断他的手指?
-Yeah.  -So, why didn't you break his thumb like I told you to?
你不照我意思做  我很丢脸啊
When you don't do what I tell you to do, you make me look bad, Rock.
我想...如果打断了他手指
I figured...look, I figured if I break the guy's thumb,
他没工开  就不能赚钱...
he gets laid off, right? Then he can't make...
这些事不用你伤脑筋...
Don't figure...let me do the figurin', okay, Rock?
由现在开始  你不要想这些
From here on in, just let me do the figurin', you know?
这些人以为我们搞慈善
These guys think that we're runnin' some kind of charity or somethin'.
以为不会受罚
That they can get off light.
总之从今日起  照我说话做
From here on in, do what I tell you to do
不然我名誉会受损  你明白吗?
because it's bad for my reputation, you understand?
明白没...洛奇?
You got... You got it, Rock?
明白
I got it.
度里奥   怎样写?
Hey, how do you spell Del Rio?
-自己查字典吧!   -不要这样
-Open a dictionary, Rock!  -Come on!
以后我会照你意思  关于手指的事
Hey, I won't let that happen no more...about the thumb.
你知道吗?
You know?
再见  肉球
So long, meatbag.
我应该打断你手指
I should've broke your thumbs!
洛奇  听说你昨晚打得很好
Hey, Rock, heard you did real good last night.
绝对是  你应该来看
Absolutely. You should've seen me.
你不用休息吗?
Don't you think you oughta take a rest?
-不  我背脊受了伤  -背脊?
-No, my back is hurtin'.  -Your back?
我背脊受了伤  你聋了吗?
My back is hurtin'. You deaf?
不  我只是矮
No, I'm short.
喂  迈克
Hey, yo, Mike,
我的锁呢?  我柜里的东西是谁的?
where's my lock? Whose stuff is this in my locker?
是迪柏的东西  这已不是你的储物柜
It's Dipper's stuff. It ain't your locker no more.
什么意思?
What you talkin' 'bout, it ain't my locker?
我用了这柜六年  我的衣服呢?
It's been my locker for six years. Where's my gear?
米克叫我装好挂起
Mickey told me to bag it and hang it.
你把我的东西放到徙置区
You put my stuff on skid row.
那储物柜我用了六年了
I been in that locker for six years
你居然把我的东西放到徙置区?
and you put my stuff in a bag on skid row?
米克吩咐的  我只是照做
Mickey tells me what to do, I gotta do it, right, Rock?
他在哪里?
Where is he?
他在教迪柏练拳
He's outside working with Dipper.
-他心情不好  -我也是
-He's in a bad mood.  -So am I.
双手抬高  双手抬高  留意右面
Get your hands up there. Keep your hands up. That's right.
-嘿  米克  -闭嘴!
-Hey, Mick.  -Shut up!
打在身上  对了
To the body. To the body. Attaboy.
够点  够点了
Time. Time!
你想怎样?
The hell. What do you want?
你今天觉得怎样?
How're you feelin' today?
-什么?  -你觉得怎样?
-What?  -I said, how're you feelin'?
-你是医生?  -你今天有病?
-What are you...a doctor?  -You got problems today?
与你无关...你有什么问题?
Never mind my problem...what's your problem?
迈克跟我说了
My problem is I've been talking to your man Michael.
干吗拿走我的储物柜?
I wanna know how come I've been put out of my locker.
因为迪柏需要个柜  迪柏可以争冠军
Because Dipper needed it. Dipper's a contender.
他是奋斗型  你呢?
He's a climber. You know what you are?
-什么?  -你是番茄
-What?  -You're a tomato.
-番茄?  -是的  面对它吧
-A tomato?  -Yeah, let's face it.
我这里是做生意的  不是慈善饭堂
I run a business here, not a goddamn soup kitchen.
-你昨晚有拳赛吗?  -有
-Did you fight last night?  -Yeah.
-有无赢?  -有  第二回合击倒对手胜出
-Did you win?  -Yeah, I won. Kayo in the second.
是?  对手是谁?
Yeah? Who'd you fight?
史派德·烈高
Spider Rico.
他是废柴
He's a bum.
你觉得我所有对手都是废柴
You think everybody I fight is a bum.
不是吗?
Well, ain't they?
你有斗心  但你的拳法像猩猩
You got heart, but you fight like a goddamn ape.
你特别之处是你从未被人打爆鼻子
Nothing special about you. You never got your nose busted.
就好好保持你个靓样...和你剩余的脑袋
Well, leave it that way... nice and pretty, and what's left of your mind.
你知道的  米克  我很愤怒
You know, Mick, I think I'm gonna go take a steam.
知道为什么吗?  因为我昨晚打得好好  你应该来看
You know why? 'Cause I did real good last night, and you should've seen me.
-没什么了不起  -你也应该来看
-Big deal.  -You should've seen me, too.
喂  你有没有想过不再打拳?
Hey, kid. You ever think about retiring?
-没有  -想想吧
-No.  -You think about it.
-好  -好了  够点
-Yeah.  -All right. Time.
-嘿  老弟  -什么事?
-Hey, man.  -What?
我很喜欢你的储物柜
I dig your locker, man.
喜欢你的储物柜
I dig your locker.
打得好
Attaboy.
今晚好冷
Cold night.
很容易患肺炎的  知道吗?
Good night to catch pneumonia, you know?
你要帮手吗?
You need some help with that cage?
今晚在费城球场有场很精彩的赛事
There's a good game down at the Spectrum tonight.
你有兴趣看篮球赛吗?
Wanna go to a basketball game?
嗨  毕寇斯
Hi, Butkus. Hi, kid.
今天真倒霉  他们取走了我的储物柜
Tough day today, you know. They took my locker away.
我用了那柜六年  不过我不介意
I had that locker for about six years, but it don't bother me none.
储物柜用久了也不好
Lockers are bad, anyway.
他们知道你的密码
After a while, people get the combination.
过去六年我一定被人偷了20元
I must've had 20 bucks taken out of there in the past six years.
听来不是很多钱  但小数怕长计
It don't sound like much, but it adds up, you know.
算了吧  谁在乎?
Doesn't matter. Who cares.
很冷的晚上呢
Wow. Cold night.
嘿  雀仔!  看这是谁
Hey, birds! Hey, look who's here.
看这是谁  巨型蚯蚓
Look who's here. The giant worm.
看这些雀
Look at these birds.
这些鸟儿看起来不像糖吗?  飞起来像糖
Don't these birds look like candy, you know? Like flying candy.
雀仔  你载我飞回家好吗?
Hey, bird, you wanna fly me home?
你需要人送你回家吗?
You need somebody to walk you home?
-不用  -不用?  今晚很冷
-No.  -No? It's a cold night.
有钱的话就坐的士
If I was you and you got the money, I would take a cab or something.
这区很多烂仔
Too many creeps around here, you know.
每个街口都有一个
Every other block, there's a creep.
烂仔一看就知
You can always tell a creep.
好的  我走先  好吗?
All right. Listen, I'm gonna go now, okay?
迟些见
I'll see yous later, all right?
你们个个都在睡
Don't any of you guys get up.
整天在笼里很辛苦吧
I know you had a hard day in the cage.
那...我回家想个新笑话
So, uh...I'm gonna go home, make up a joke.
明天告诉你  晚安  艾莉
I'm gonna tell you a new joke tomorrow, okay? Good night, Adrian.
晚安  洛奇
Good night, Rocky.
幸运七星酒馆
不知发生什么事
I don't know what happens to me.
嘿  左撇子
Hey there, Lefty.
-这个是你朋友  -你好  洛奇
-I got a friend for you.  -Hello, Rock.
你好吗?  你见过保利吗?
How you doin'? You seen Paulie?
-有  他在蒸气房  -是吗
-Yeah, he's in the steam room.  -Yeah?
洛奇  你眼睛怎么了?
Hey, Rocky, what's with the eye?
-打拳弄伤的  -希望你至少打赢了
-Been fightin'.  -Hope you won it, at least.
是  我打得很好  你应该来看
Yeah, I did real good. You should've seen me.
世界重量级拳王阿波罗·奎迪
Heavyweight champion of the world Apollo Creed
在肯尼迪机场  纽约
is at Kennedy Airport, New York.
洛奇  你昨晚对谁?
Hey, Rocky, who'd you fight?
史派德·烈高
Spider Rico.
天呀  他还有打的吗?
Is he still around?
是  他状态很好  好过你
Yeah, he's doing real good. He's doing better than you... that's for sure.
嘿  保利  你锁了门?
Hey, Paulie, what, did you lock the door?
喂  保利!
Yo, Paulie!
我要杀了那打烂镜子的白痴
I'd like to kill the freakin' moron who broke the mirror.
喂  保利
Hey, yo, Paulie,
我每天早晚去
every day, every night I pass by
你妹妹店里  她都冷落我
your sister's giving me the shoulder, you know what I mean?
-忘记她吧  -什么意思?
-Forget her.  -What do you mean, forget her?
-你可以找到好过她的  -我不会
-You can do better than her.  -Forget nothin'.
每晚我都去  说个笑话
Every night I pass by the place, I tell a joke.
每早我又去  说个笑话
Every morning I pass by the place, I tell a joke. Nothing.
她只是看着我  你懂我意思吗?
She just looks at me, you know what I mean?
-看?  -是  当我是一碟隔夜菜
-Looks, huh?  -Yeah, like I'm a plate of leftovers.
是否要有靓车她才会睬我?
What...I need a Cadillac to connect with your sister?
还是我样子有问题?
Something wrong with my face? You know what I mean?
她是个废物
She's a freakin' loser.
有时她令我发狂到想用剃刀劈开她的头
Sometimes she gets me so crazy, I could split her head with a razor.
不要发癫了
Don't get mental, man, you know.
-你遇着我心情差  -你永远心情差
-Well, you caught me in a bad mood. -You're always in a bad mood.
艾莉好蠢  艾莉是个白痴
Adrian ain't sharp. Adrian is a loser.
-嘿  -都奔30岁的人了
-Hey. -She's pushin' 30 freakin' years old.
她再不上心  就会孤独老死
And if she don't watch out, she's gonna end up dying alone.
-我自己都30岁  -你也会孤独老死
-I'm 30 myself.  -Then you're gonna end up dying alone.
你也不见得会有人陪
Hey, I don't need see no crowd around you, neither.
我要杀了那打烂镜子的白痴
I'd like to kill the freakin' moron who broke the mirror.
来  我们离开这臭地方
Come on, let's get out of this stink, would you? Come on.
-好  横竖我要跟你谈谈  -关于什么?
-I wanna talk to you anyway.  -About what?
-你还有帮加索做事吗?  -有
-You still work for Gazzo?  -Yeah, sure.
你可否向加索推荐我?
Why don't you talk to him about me?
但加索现在不请人
Well, I just don't think Gazzo's hirin' right now, you know? You know?
来吧
Come on.
-她越来越萎缩  -谁?
-The girl's dryin' up.  -Who?
我妹妹  她再不开始生活 身体就会萎缩掉
My sister. If she don't start livin', her body's gonna dry up.
明天是感恩节  知道吗?
You know, tomorrow's Thanksgiving, you know that?
为什么不过来跟她倾诉?
Why don't you come over and talk to her?
好的  啤酒
Sure. Beer.
明天你来吃火鸡  好吗?
Tomorrow you come for some bird, right?
当然好  我会来
Absolutely. You got it.
我要走了  我只要迟十分钟  她就去问医院
I gotta go. If I'm ten minutes late, she calls the hospital.
-保利!  -我来
-Paulie!  -I got it. I got it.
...200周年纪念赛对麦克·李·格林在费城的
Bicentennial fight with Mac Lee Green here in Philadelphia
费城球场  拉里?
at the fabulous Spectrum. Harry?
这是备受瞩目的200周年纪念赛
We're speaking now of your much publicized bicentennial fight.
对  这将是。。。
That's right, this is gonna be
本国史上最大的体坛盛事
the greatest sporting event in the country's history.
在这庆典里 我会当格林是罪犯般击败
A gala occurrence with me beating Green like he committed a crime.
你看那人?
Would you take a look at that guy?
真正的拳手从哪里来的?
I mean, where are the real fighters gonna come from?
那些专业的  现在只有那些黑人小丑
The pros. All we got today are jig clowns.
在1月1日  本国最大盛事...
On January 1st, the first major event in the country...
-小丑?  -对  小丑
-Clowns?  -That's right. Clowns.
像史上所有大型赛事
And in keeping with great events throughout the country's history.
阿波罗·奎迪会
Apollo Creed will duplicate the cracking of the liberty bell
击碎格林
by cracking Mac Lee Green.
你说阿波罗·奎迪是小丑?
You callin' Apollo Creed a clown?
当然啦  看他
Well, what else? Look at him.
努力求学  认真思考
Stay in school and use your brain.
做医生  律师  拿皮制公事包
Be a doctor, be a lawyer, carry a leather briefcase.
不要做专业运动员
Forget about sports as a profession.
运动令你发牢骚和发臭
Sports make you grunt and smell.
-要食脑  不要食屎  -谢谢你  拳王
-See, be a thinker, not a stinker. -Okay, thanks a lot, Champ.
你傻了?  他是世界拳王
Hey, are you crazy? This man is champion of the world.
他努力打出最佳水准才成为拳王
He took his best shot and became champ. Huh?
你努力过什么?
What shot did you ever take?
洛奇 你不满意自己的生活  是你的事
Hey, Rocky, you're not happy with your life, it's nice.
但我有盘生意  不用去努力
But me, I got a business going. I don't have to take no shots.
他没一个对手能捱过...
No one having gone more than...
对了
That's right.
给你的生意
Stick that up your business.
你干吗那样恼?
What are you so insulted about?
你想我努力?  好...我努力喝一杯
Want me to take a shot? All right... I'll take a shot.
洛奇  最近怎样?
Rocky, how's it been going?
嗨  洛奇  来一瓶?
Hey, Rocky, how 'bout a bottle?
-不喝了  -来吧  就一点.
-No wine.  -Come on. Just a little.
玛丽  你哥哥知道你在外面逛这么晚吗?
Marie, does your brother know you're hanging out so late?
-去你的!  -她哥哥知道的
-Screw you, Go-go.  -Her brother knows.
这些家伙就这样教你说话?
Hey, these guys teach you to talk like that?
-吃狗屎吧!  -不许这样跟我说话
-Stuff it, man!  -Never say that! Come here!
你把附近都搞臭了!
You stink up the neighborhood!
-你知道你可以...  -嘿!
-You know, you can... -Hey!
我像你这么大时
When I was your age,
附近只有一个女孩说脏话
there was only one girl in the whole neighborhood talked like that.
是的  就只有她一个  你在干嘛?
That was it. Just one. What are you doing?
抽烟牙齿会变黄  别抽
It'll make your teeth yellow. Don't do that.
-我喜欢黄板牙!  -它还会让你口臭得像垃圾
-I like yellow teeth.  -It'll make your breath like garbage.
-兴许我喜欢垃圾  -别这样  没人喜欢垃圾
-Maybe I like garbage. -Come on, nobody likes garbage.
不过这个满嘴脏话的女孩长得还不赖
Anyway, this girl with the dirty mouth...she wasn't bad-lookin',
可是没有男生瞧得起她
but, you see, none of the guys ever took her seriously, see.
他们从不约她出去
They never took her out for any serious datin'.
-为什么?  -因为男生就是这样的
-Why?  -'Cause that's the way guys are.
你说粗话时他们会笑 他们觉得你很可爱
They laugh when you talk dirty, they think you're cute,
过不多久  你就名声在外了
but after a while, you get a reputation, that's it.
没人会尊重你  明白吗?
You get no respect, you understand?
没人尊重你  我要用一个坏字眼
You get no respect. And I gotta use a bad word.
婊子  婊子  明白吗?
Whore. You understand? Whore.
明白吗?  说粗话的下场
See, you use dirty words
就是可能沦为婊子
and maybe you end up becoming a whore, you understand?
拜托  洛奇  我已十二岁了
Come on, Rocky. I'm just 12.
这与你十二岁没有关系
Hey, that don't matter that you're 12. It don't matter.
你不一定真的要当婊子 行为举止像就完了
You don't really have to be one. You just act like one...that's it. Boom.
你就会臭名远播  懂不懂?
Hey, if you get a bad rap, you understand?
二十年后人们会说...
Twenty years from now, people are gonna say,
你还记得玛丽吗?
"Hey, you remember Marie?"
不  她是谁?
"No, who's she?"
就是那个在街角鬼混的小婊子
"She's the little whore that hung out at the Atomic Hoagie Shop."
噢  我现在想起来了
"Oh, yeah. Yeah, yeah, now I remember her."
看见了吧  人们不会记得你 只会记得你的名声
You see, they don't remember you, they remember the rep.
明白了吧?
You understand?
有男朋友吗?
Hey, you got a boyfriend?
不  你找不到男朋友
No, you ain't got a boyfriend.
知道为什么?  你可曾想过没有男朋友的原因?
You know why? Why don't you think you have a boyfriend?
因为你和这些街上的痞子鬼混
'Cause you're hangin' out with them coconuts in the corner, understand?
和街上的痞子鬼混没有前途
You hang around coconuts, you get nowhere.
他们一无是处
They're lemons. Lemons.
与好人交往就会有好的朋友
You hang out with nice people, you get nice friends, you understand?
与聪明人交往就会有聪明的朋友
You hang out with smart people, you get smart friends.
与混混交往就会有混混的朋友
You hang out with yo-yo people, you get yo-yo friends.
这个道理很简单
You see? It's simple mathematics.
-我希望你不会...  -我不会的
-I hope you ain't...  -I won't.
我说的重点是什么?
What was I gonna say?
你希望我不要学婊子的样子 否则我就会成为婊子 是吧?
You hope I don't keep acting like a whore, or I'll turn into one, right?
-是的  就是这样  -晚安  洛奇
-Yeah, something like that. -Good night, Rocky.
晚安  保重
Good night, Marie. Take care, you know?
嗨  洛奇  去你的  鬼样!
Hey, Rocky? Yo. Screw you, creep-o!
对  你凭什么给人忠告 你只是个鬼样
Yeah, who are you to give advice, creep-o? Huh?
你以为你是谁?
Who are you?
-医生确诊了?  -确诊了
-Are the doctor's reports confirmed?  -Definitely.
上面说麦克·李·格林
It says here Mac Lee Green has suffered
左掌第三根骨头严重骨折
a severely cracked third metacarpal in his left hand.
该死
Damn.
我们可以无限期延后日期
Of course, we can cancel the fight indefinitely
如果你坚持要与他比赛
if you're set on fighting Green.
这不只是格林的问题
Hey, it ain't just Green!
阿波罗投入的时间呢?
What about all the time Apollo has invested?
我们能找出解决之道
I believe we can find a solution.
解决个屁   你最好尽快再找个旗鼓相当的人
Solution nothin'. You better find me another ranked contender.
我的意思是太戏剧化  休根斯
And I mean in a flash, Jergens.
别跟我的客户耍花样
Don't play games with my client.
阿波罗已花了一百万宣传费
Apollo's already done a million dollars worth of publicity,
并且有履行这个牵涉到 20个不同组织的合约的义务
has made contractual obligations with 20 different organizations...
他绝不能丢脸!
he's not going to be embarrassed!
我联络厄尼·罗曼的经纪人
I contacted Ernie Roman's manager.
他同一周在法国比赛
Ernie's fighting in France that same week.
那就找巴帝·萧  他排名第五
Then get me Buddy Shaw! Hell, he's ranked fifth!
搬到加州去了   而且胖了50磅
Went to California and gained 50 pounds.
我找遍了所有可能的对手
I get a hold of every worthwhile contender
他们都说
and they all say the same thing...
五周时间不够他们准备
five weeks just isn't enough time to get into shape.
准备个屁!  是他们怕了
Shape nothin', man! They're afraid.
他们知道全世界会看到这场拳赛
They know everybody in the world's gonna see this fight,
没有一个人能击败我
and none of them's got a prayer of whippin' me.
所以找借口避免被我修理
They're makin' excuses so they don't have to be the chump
怕在全世界观众面前丢脸
to get whipped in front of the whole civilized world.
我只能说我是个好的主办者
All I can say is I'm a good promoter.
我在世界各国主办无数拳赛
I've promoted fights in every goddamn country in the world,
我却在这场拳赛阴沟里翻船
and I've broken my ass over this one.
我已黔驴技穷!
But I don't know what the hell else to do!
我有办法
I do.
既然没有排名内的选手
Without a ranked contender,
这场比赛就需要些创新
what this fight is gonna need is a novelty.
这是个充满机会的地方  对吧?
This is the land of opportunity, right?
所以阿波罗·奎迪在元旦当天...
So Apollo Creed, on January 1st,
给当地毫无胜算的人一个机会
gives a local underdog fighter an opportunity.
一个名不见经传的小子
A snow-white underdog,
我要他的照片跟我一起登上海报
and I'm gonna put his face on this poster with me.
我告诉你们为什么
And I'll tell you why.
因为我多愁善感
Because I'm sentimental.
这个国家有许许多多多愁善感的人
And a lot of other people in this country are just as sentimental,
没有比在这个世界上最重大的节日里
and there's nothing they'd like better than to see Apollo Creed
看到阿波罗·奎迪让当地男孩有机会出赛
give a local Philadelphia boy
而在最大盛事时更让他们高兴的事
a shot at the greatest title in the world on this country's biggest birthday.
这就是我的看法
Now, that's the way I see it.
而且赛事就要如此进行
And that's the way it's gonna be.
阿波罗  我喜欢
Apollo, I like it.
很有有美国味
It's very American.
不 休根斯
No, Jergens.
是非常聪明
It's very smart.
好的  晚些时候见
Okay, I'll see you later, man.
-怎么了?  -我只是要确认一下
-What? What is it?  -I just wanna check this thing out.
你说向史奈德收二百
Now, you said pick up two yards from Snyder
卡波里收一千
and a grand from Cappoli, right?
不对  卡波里收二百 史奈德收一千
No, no. No, no. Two yards from Cappoli and a grand from Snyder.
-两百  -记下来  好吗?
-Two yards. Two yards.  -Write it down, okay?
好  我记下来了
Yeah, I got it. Got it.
明晚和你约会的女孩是谁?
Who's this girl you're going out with tomorrow night?
你怎么知道?
How'd you know?
你以为我不知道吗?  我有很多消息来源
You know.Don't you think I hear things?A lot of canaries flying around the docks.
-我要和保利的妹妹出去  -嗨  洛奇
-I'm going out with Paulie's sister.  -Hey, Rocky.
-嗯?  -听说她是弱智
-What? -I hear she's retarded.
她不是弱智  只是害羞而已
She ain't retarded. She's shy, you know?
告诉你怎么做
I'll tell you what to do.
带她去动物园  听说弱智喜欢动物园
Take her to the zoo. I hear retards like the zoo.
-你这无赖一定要这么说话吗?  -你说谁呢?
-This bum gotta say that?  -Who're you calling a bum?
-靠后点  我说你是无赖!  -别激动
-I'm calling you a bum!  -Okay, relax. Relax.
他心情不好 前列腺有毛病
Buddy's in a bad mood. It's his prostate.
他老是心情不好
He's always in a bad mood.
你应该多积点口德
You know, you oughta count your blessings, Buddy.
趁你现在还很健康
You're still a healthy person, you know that?
-我不喜欢你的样子  -我也不喜欢你的!
-I don't like your face. -I don't like yours, either!
-去你的!  -别这样
-Kiss my ass!  -Move your shoulders down!
-下车  -别激动  我耳朵受不了
-Get out of the car! -Relax, relax! Relax. My ears.
你们两个快让我发疯了
What, are you driving me crazy? Both of yous.
-他不喜欢你  -是的
-Buddy doesn't like you.  -Yeah.
有些人就是看别人不顺眼
Some guys, they just hate for no reason, capisce?
-是的  -过来
-Yeah.  -Come here.
这里有五十元 你和艾莉去好好玩一玩
There's 50 bucks. You and your girl Adrian have a nice time, you hear?
谢谢
Thanks.
你怎会知道她的名字?
Hey, how'd you know her name?
你以为我不知道吗?
You don't think I hear things?
-嗨  洛奇  -嗯?
-Hey, Rock.  -What?
-记住我说的话  -什么话?
-Remember what I told you.  -What'd you tell me?
带她去动物园
Take her to the zoo.
-奎迪先生  要多些咖啡吗  -不用了 谢谢 雪莉
-Some more coffee, Mr. Creed? -No, thanks, Shirley.
你觉得比利·史奴怎样?
What do you think about Billy Snow?
不行
Fouls.
卓·史密夫呢?
How 'bout Big Chuck Smith?
-是啊  -不  他太老和太闷
-Yeah.  -Nah. He's too old and dull.
那波比·祖治  是好男孩
Hey, Bobby Judd. He's a good boy.
不  那名字太无瘾
No, I don't feel any heat from that name.
可以考虑祖·萨克
Joe Zach's a good prospect.
阿波罗  到底你要找怎样的?
Exactly what are you looking for, Apollo?
这就是我要找的
This is what I'm looking for.
意大利牡马
The Italian Stallion.
洛奇·巴尔博亚?  没听过这个人
Rocky Balboa? Never heard of him.
是那名字
Look, it's the name, man.
意大利牡马  传媒一定喜欢
The Italian Stallion. The media will eat it up.
是谁发现美国?  意大利人  对吗?
Now, who discovered America? An Italian, right?
有什么好得过跟他的后人比赛?
What would be better than to get it on with one of his descendents?
他是个左撇子
He's a southpaw.
我不想你浪费时间跟左撇子打
I don't want you messing around with southpaws.
-他们做什么都反转  -左撇子没问题
-They do everything backwards.  -Southpaw nothin'.
我三个回合可打败他
I'll drop him in three.
阿波罗·奎迪对意大利牡马
Apollo Creed meets the Italian Stallion.
听上去好像一套怪兽电影
Sounds like a damn monster movie.
你拿着球棒干什么?
Hey, what are you doing with that bat, huh?
我以前打棒球好劲  你妹妹知道我会来?
I used to be deadly at stickball. You sure your sister knows I'm comin'?
她很高兴
She's very excited.
-看我的手肿了  -是
-Look at my swollen hands. -Yeah.
把肉从冰柜搬进搬出
The joints from walkin' and carryin' meat in and out of freezers.
弄坏了关节
It plays hell on the joints.
你应该去看医生
Maybe you oughta see a doctor. What do you think?
我不需要看医生  我需要转工
I don't need a doctor. I need a different job.
转工  是怎样的火鸡?  大还是小?
Different job. What kind of turkey? Big turkey or small turkey?
跟加索谈谈  说我人品不错
Talk to Gazzo about me. Tell him I'm a good man and nothin' bothers me.
我什么都做  我会好好的收帐  打断人骨头没问题
I'd make a great collector. Bustin' bones don't bother me.
不想烦你  是大火鸡吧?
Don't bother you. A big turkey, right? Huh?
-加索会给我...  -忘记加索  那份工不好做
-Gazzo's gotta come...  -forget Gazzo. It's a bad job, you know what I mean?
-你有火柴吗?  -替我找他  当帮我
-You got a match?  -Go to him for me. As a favor.
是  上次我吃火鸡
Yeah. Yeah. You know, the last time I had a turkey
是做两元特价时
was when they were having a $2 special
三年前在康哈达自助餐厅
at Horn and Hardog's about three years ago.
去年  我和龟仔们吃了午餐肉
Last year me and the turtles had spam. What do you think?
是的  听起来是个好主意
Yeah, that sounds like a good idea.
你妹妹真的知道我来?
Your sister knows I'm coming for sure, right?
知道  她很高兴
Yeah, yeah. She's very excited.
我一直很孤单
I'm all alone
你忘记加索好吗?
Hey, will you forget about Gazzo, huh?
-我很少求人两次  -很少求人两次
-I don't ask nobody twice. -I don't ask nobody twice.
走开
Stay away, baby
你肯定你妹妹知道我来?
Hey, your sister...you sure your sister knows I'm comin'?
是呀  她非常高兴
Yeah, yeah, yeah. She's very excited.
真的吗?
Yeah?
保利?  你迟了回来
Paulie? You're late.
你打去医院了?  我迟十分钟她就会打去医院
Called the hospital? She calls the hospital if I'm ten minutes late.
你好吗?
How you doin'?
一早说了  她很高兴
I told you she's very excited.
你为什么不告诉我他会来?
Paulie, why didn't you tell me you were bringing him here?
我无心理准备
Look at me. I'm not ready for this.
你有准备又有什么分别?
Would it make a difference if you were?
他会带你出去
He's a friend, and now he's taking you out.
不  我不会去
No, I can't.
我要你立即离开厨房
You're in the kitchen, and I want you out right now.
你立即出来
Hey, I want you outta here instamatically!
我厌倦了看着你像蜘蛛般孵在屋里
I'm sick of seein' you hanging around like a freakin' spider!
快出去  享受生命
Go out! Live! Enjoy life!
我不能去
Paulie, I can't go!
你不要在我面前扮高贵
Don't get wise with me, now, huh?
-我受够了你那么无用  -不要说我无用  保利
-I'm tired of you being a loser. -Don't call me that, Paulie!
阿波罗·奎迪说他会找另一个牺牲者
Apollo Creed says he'll be shopping for another victim
在200周年纪念冠军赛里 填补格林的空缺...
to fill Green's vacancy for the bicentennial championship fight.
你干吗不告诉我他会来?
Why didn't you tell me you were bringing him home?
-你怎知我没说?  -我不能去
-How do you know I didn't? -I'm not gonna go, Paulie! I can't go!
-我不会去!  -为什么?
-I won't go!  -Why?!
今天是感恩节  我焗了火鸡
Paulie, it's Thanksgivin'. I got a turkey in the oven.
噢  焗了火鸡
Oh. A turkey in the oven?
焗了火鸡
A turkey in the oven.
你想吃火鸡?
You want the bird?
去后巷吃吧
Go in the alley and eat the bird.
噢  保利
Oh, Paulie.
我要你出去 离开这间屋
I want you outta here! Get outta the house!
出去好好享受生命
Go out and enjoy your freakin' life!
洛奇  你肚饿吗?
You hungry, Rock?
保利  今天不如算了吧?
Yo, Paulie, listen. Maybe we just better forget all this, you know?
-算了吧   -算个屁
-Just forget it. -Forget nothin'.
去  跟她说笑话
Go ahead. Tell her somethin' funny.
没什么好说的  她心情不好 我又心情不好
Ain't nothin' to talk about. She's in a bad mood, I'm in a bad mood.
你可以搞笑的 你不是想跟她约会吗?
You know how to do funny. You wanna go out with my sister?
-是的  -那就加油啊...
-Yeah.  -Well... come on.
-我不知说什么好  -要搞笑
-I don't know what to say.  -Funny
艾莉  是我  洛奇
Yo, Adrian, it's me, Rocky.
洛奇  知吗?
Rocky, you know?
听着
Listen, uh...
我不知说什么好
I don't know what to say,
因为我未试过跟门说话
'cause I ain't never talked to no door before, you know?
我应该跟道门说什么?  嘿  听着...
I mean, what do I say to a door... hey, listen...
你做得很好
Come on. You're doin' fine.
我做得不好  我似个白痴
I ain't doin' fine. I look like an idiot.
继续啦  搞笑
Keep doin' what you're doin'. You're funny.
这方面我最在行
I know all about these things.
我像个傻佬
I feel like a jerk.
艾莉  又是我  洛奇
Yo, Adrian, it's Rocky again, you know?
我知你现在不开心
Listen, uh... I know you ain't too happy at this moment, you know,
但可否帮我一个忙?
but could you do me a favor?
没人陪我过感恩节
I ain't got nobody to spend Thanksgiving with, you know?
不如
So, uh...
你跟我一起出去吃顿饭
how 'bout maybe you and I maybe go out together, get something to eat.
我不知道  或者笑笑  知道吗?
I don't know. Maybe laugh a little bit. Who knows, you know?
你会否想...
Would you like to, uh...
你会否想跟我出去?
I don't know. Would you like to maybe, you know, you and me go out together?
怎样?  好吗?
What do you think? Would you like to?
我们会玩得很开心的
We're gonna have a good time.
会玩得很开心的
We'll have a real good time.
谢谢你的火鸡
Thanks for the bird.
我要关掉电视  头痛死了
I'm gonna turn the TV off. I got a headache.
-你妹妹喜欢做什么?  -溜冰
-What does your sister like to do?  -Ice skate.
艾莉  来吧  暖气都走了
Adrian, come on. You're lettin' the heat out.
还不是我付的帐单?
Who pays the bills around here?
反正我不想吃火鸡
Listen, I don't want no turkey anyway, you know?
但今天是感恩节
But it was Thanksgiving.
-什么?  -感恩节
-It was what?  -It was Thanksgiving.
是  对你来说  但对我来说是星期四
Yeah, to you. But to me it's Thursday.
-很静呢  -好像关门了
-It looks kinda quiet, you know?  -I think it's closed.
不  大概是我们太早
No, I think maybe we're just early or something like that.
-我们关门了  -什么?
-We're closed. -What?
我们休息
I said we're closed.
听着  我去跟他谈妥
Yeah. Hey, listen, I'm gonna smooth this guy out here.
你等等 我很快回来 好吗?
So just wait here for a few minutes. I'll be right back, okay?
-我们可以去别处  -不  没问题
-We could go someplace else.  -No, it's okay.
你是不开放给公众
Hey, listen, are you closed to the general public,
还是不开放给所有人...你知道我的意思?
or are you closed to everybody...you know what I mean?
已过了6点  今天是感恩节 所以没人来
Look, it's after 6:00, it's Thanksgiving. That's why there's nobody here.
况且  你不应该进来
And besides, you ain't supposed to be in here.
所以麻烦你出去
So do me a favor and not stay here, huh?
-你可否帮个忙? -不要这样  我们现在不开门
-Would you do me a favor? -Hey, come on. We're not operatin'.
这位小姐有病在身
Look...this girl here ain't feelin' well, you know.
医生说她要多做运动
The doctors say she should go out and exercise once in a while,
溜冰是最佳选择
and ice skating's probably the best thing, know what I mean?
那你想怎样?
So what do you want from me?
我想你帮忙  你都看见她有病
I want you to do me a favor. You could see she ain't feelin' too good.
如果你让她溜几分钟  我会很感激
If you could let her on the ice, I'd appreciate it. For a few minutes.
十分钟  十元
Ten minutes, ten bucks.
十元?  八元可以吗?
Ten bucks? How 'bout eight... eight bucks?
不要讲价  感恩节嘛
Come on. It's Thanksgiving.
-好吧  九元  一口价  -十元  整个场任你玩
-All right, nine bucks, you got a deal. -You have the ice to yourself. Ten bucks.
拿溜冰鞋给她
Give her the blades.
你不溜冰吗?
Aren't you skating?
我15岁开始便没溜过冰
Nah. I ain't skated since I was 15.
那时我开始打拳
That's when I started fightin'...when I was 15.
溜冰会令足踝受损
Skating's kinda bad for the ankles, you know?
你很会溜冰  是吗?
You're a pretty good skater, are you?
正如我刚才说
You know, like I was saying before on the way over here.
以前我把打拳放在首位  但不再是
Fightin' used to be tops with me, but no more, you know?
我只想用打拳来证明我不是废柴
All I wanted to do at a fight was prove I was no bum...
我有本事做出色的专业拳手
that I had the stuff to make a good pro, you know?
你一直没有机会?
You never got the chance?
我没抱怨  我依然打拳  当它是嗜好
Hey, I ain't cryin' about it, 'cause I still fight. I kinda do it like a hobby.
问题是我是 南泽西
I tell you what the trouble is...I'm a southpaw.
-什么是南泽西?  -即是左撇子
-What's a southpaw?  -A southpaw means you're left-handed.
南泽西较难掌握时间
And a southpaw throws your timing off, you see.
令对手也掌握不到时间 看上去很笨拙
Other guys it throws their timing off, makes them look awkward.
没人想让人觉得笨拙
Nobody wants to look awkward.
-你知道南泽西的来由吗?  -九分钟
-You know where southpaw came from?  -Nine minutes!
很久以前有个人  大概两百年前
I'll tell ya. A long time ago, this guy...maybe a couple hundred years ago...
他在费城打拳
he was fightin' in the...I think it was around Philadelphia...
他的手...  他是用左手的
and his arm... he was left-handed,
他的手向着新泽西  那是南面
and his arm was facing towards New Jersey, you see, and that's south.
所以人们叫他做南泽西
So then that's why they call 'em southpaw, you see?
南泽西  南肯顿
Southpaw, South Jersey. South Camden,
南泽西  你明白吗?
southpaw. You know what I mean?
或者这样也好
I don't know. Things probably worked out for the best, don't you think?
因为是左撇子而没机会?
Never got a chance, though, because you're left-handed, huh?
那是实情  小心
Well, that's absolutely true, you know. Watch out.
啊 啊 我的手指脱了臼
I just dislocated my finger.
啊 看  慢着  不关你事  看
Look at that. No, wait. Hey, it ain't your fault. Look.
看见吗?  那是旧伤口
See? Look, I had it...it's an old wound, you see that?
看见吗?  没事的  可以那样弯
Look. See? Nothin'. It bends like that, see?
我本来是... 按钮
I originally done it... look, push the button.
搞掂  不关你事
-Bong. It works. It ain't your fault. Look, I'm gonna show you somethin'.
七分钟
-Seven minutes!
我本来是...我带着我所有拳赛的照片
Yeah, I originally done it. I carry pictures of all my fights.
那本来是 在跟宝贝·坚沙的比赛中弄伤的
I originally done it in the Baby Crenshaw fight. See that?
宝贝像飞机那样大只 我两只手都在打他脸部时断了骨
Big Baby's about the size of an airplane. I broke both my hands on his face.
我输了那场拳赛  但这张相很好 你觉得呢?
I lost that fight,but that's a nice picture,don't you think?See how it works there?
真的很好
Real nice.
你玩得开心吗?
Come on. You having a good time?
我动作不是很优美
I'll tell you...you could see I ain't too graceful. I don't move well.
我动作生硬  但我出拳可以很重
But I'll tell you, I can really swat, you know what I mean? I can really hit hard.
不过我是南泽西  没人喜欢跟南泽西打
But I'm a southpaw, and nobody wants to fight no southpaw, know what mean?
你知我是怎样开始打拳的吗?
You know how I got started in fightin'?
不知道
No.
我是不是太大声?
Am I talkin' too loud?
-不  -三分钟!
-No.  -Three minutes!
我爸爸...不是太聪明
My father... he's, uh... my old man, he was never too smart.
他跟我说  你天生没有脑
He says to me, "You weren't born with much of a brain,
所以要用身体
so you better start using your body," right?
于是我做了拳手
So I become a fighter.
-你明我意思吗?  -是的
-You know what I mean? -Yeah.
你笑什么?
Why are you... why are you laughin'?
我母亲说的刚刚相反
My mother... she said the opposite thing.
她说什么相反?
What'd she say? What'd she say, the opposite?
她说   你天生身体不好
She said you weren't born with much of a body,
所以要用脑
so you better develop your brain.
她真的那样说?
Did she say that?
喂  够点了
Yo! Time!
我可以问你一个问题吗?
Can I ask you a question?
当然可以
Absolutely.
-你为什么喜欢打拳?  -因为我不懂唱歌跳舞
-Why do you wanna fight? -'Cause I can't sing or dance.
不要跌倒
Eh, oh. Don't fall! Don't fall!
很好  我做得不错
Hey, that was terrific. I'm pretty good at this.
喜欢我这样溜冰吗?
You like the way I skate?
我上一场比赛的对手 叫史派德·烈高
The last fight I had, I had with this guy named Spider Rico.
他打到我头破血流 你看见这疤痕吗?
He busted my head up. You see that scar?
擂台上可以很粗暴
I'll tell ya... things get pretty rough in the ring.
有人生性怕羞
You know, with some people, I'm very shy by nature, you know?
大概是
I suppose.
我觉得你是生性怕羞
I say you're very shy by nature, you know?
大概是
I suppose.
躲在暗角的流浪汉
Ey! Ey. The bum from the dark.
去找份工作啦
Get a job, you bum!
有人觉得怕羞是一种病
You know, some people think that being shy is a disease,
但我不觉得有问题
but it don't bother me none.
我也不觉得
It don't bother me, either.
那我为什么要提起?
Then why'd I bother bringing it up, huh?
因为我蠢
'Cause I'm dumb, that's why.
我们是一对活宝
I think we make a real sharp couple of coconuts.
我蠢  你怕羞  你觉得呢?
I'm dumb, you're shy. What do you think, huh?
我不明白怎么会有人想做拳手
I don't understand why anybody would wanna be a fighter.
你一定要是白痴
Hey, you gotta be a moron.
才会做拳手  你知道我的意思?
You gotta be a moron to wanna be a fighter, you know what I mean?
那骗人的行业注定你最终要成为废柴
It's a racket where you're almost guaranteed to end up a bum.
-我不觉得你是废柴  -我至少是半条废柴
-I don't think you're a bum. -Well, I'm at least half a bum, you know?
但我告诉你
But I'll tell ya somethin'.
打拳最难受的  是之后那早上
The worst thing about fightin' is the mornin' after, you know?
-知吗?  -之后那早上
-The mornin' after? -I'll tell you. Yeah.
对  拳赛之后那早上  你就像个大伤口
The mornin' after a fight, you're nothing but a large wound, know what I mean?
有时全身痛
Sometimes I got pains all over me.
从床去厕所都想叫的士
I feel like callin' a taxi to take me from the bed into the bathroom.
头发痛  眼睛痛
Your hair hurts, your eyes hurt,
面部损伤  双手肿胀
your face is all busted up, your hands are swollen, you know?
看我块面  64场拳赛  看那鼻子
Look at this face. 64 fights. Look at that nose.
看见我鼻子吗?
See that nose?
鼻子被人打过  却未断过
That nose ain't never been broken. 64 fights.
被人咬过  扭过  撞过
I've had guys bustin' on it, I had guys chewin' on it,
总之劈过搥过
twistin' it, punchin' it... I mean, whack! Boom!
他们成日打我鼻子
These guys, they hittin' my nose all the time.
但从没打断过  我为此很自豪  很罕见的
Never broken. I'm very proud of that. Isn't that rare? That's rare.
-既然会受伤  为什么还要打?  -你认为呢?
-Why do you do it if it hurts? -Why do you think?
因为你不懂唱歌跳舞?
'Cause... you can't sing and dance.
对了  大概是这样
Yeah, somethin' like that. Somethin' like that.
你要进来吗?
Hey, you wanna come inside?
不  我要走了
No. I gotta go.
来吧  我有小动物
Hey, come on. Hey, I got some animals.
我里面有很珍贵的动物  进来吧
I got these rare... very rare animals inside. Come on. Come on in.
不  我要走了
No, no. I gotta go.
我也要走了  是去厕所  来吧
Well, I gotta go, too. I gotta go to the bathroom. Come on.
来啦
Come on.
不  我真的要走
-No,I gotta go.
看我的脸  很可靠吧?
-Hey,look at this face.Is that a face you could trust or what?Is it?
我这样子应该印在邮票上
They oughta stick this face on a stamp. What do you think?
来吧
Come on. Come on in.
喂  进来啦
Yo. Come on.
开灯
Click.
艾莉  你饿吗?
Yo, Adrian, are you hungry?
不
No.
我有食物  你要汽水  面包圈或什么吗?
I got some things in there. If you like soda, some donuts or something.
也有蛋糕  不要?
A couple cupcakes. Huh? No?
还有朱古力
I think I got some chocolate in there.
不要?
No?
这里很热
Hot in here, you know?
我想听音乐
I could go for some music.
艾莉
Yo, Adrian.
这些就是我说的奇异动物
These are the exotic animals I was tellin' you about.
他们是我的朋友  格夫和林肯
These are my friends Cuff and Link.
是我卖给你的
I sold 'em to you.
我知是你卖给我的
Sure, I know you sold them to me.
你记得吗?  你在那间宠物店工作
Remember you were workin' at that pet shop, huh?
你第一天上班  我进来买了这些动物
First day you was there, I came in and bought both these animals, huh?
我记得
Yeah, I remember that.
我买了这个缸和里面的动物
I came and I bought this bowl and I bought the, uh, bought the animals themselves,
一些食粮  和放缸底的石粒
some food, the marbles that go in the bottom there.
记得那座山吗?
Remember? Remember that mountain?
我要丢了那座山
I had to get rid of that mountain,
因为总是反转倒下来
though, 'cause they kept falling over and flipping.
你为什么不过来坐?
Yo, why don't you come on over here and sit down?
张梳化很好坐
It's a nice couch. I don't know.
那边有大虫  这边较安全
There's big bugs in there, you know. It's safer over here.
你要坐下吗?
You wanna sit down?
-是你父母?  -对  是我父母
-Uh, these...these your parents? -Yeah, that's...that's both of them there.
这个是你?
Is this you?
是  我那时八岁
Yeah, that's me when I was eight years old.
那就是婴儿版的意大利牡马
That's the Italian Stallion when he was a baby.
过来吧  舒服点  放松
Why don't you come on over and make yourself comfortable? Relax.
你有电话吗?
Do you have a phone?
没有  我拔了电话线
No, I ain't got no phone.
因为经常有人打来
I had it pulled 'cause of people calling all the time, and, uh,
令我很烦  骚扰我
who needs the aggravation, right? The interruptions.
你想打给谁?
Who'd you wanna call?
我想让我哥哥知道我在哪里
I wanna let my brother know where I am.
为什么?
Why?
他可能会担心我
I think he might be worried.
我可以找你哥哥  是那原因的话
Well, I'll call your brother, if that's the problem.
保利 你妹妹在我处  我迟些回复你 再见
Yo, Paulie, your sister's with me! I'll call yous back later! See ya!
你不喜欢这里  是吗?
What's the matter? You don't like the room, do ya.
很好呀
It's fine.
只是暂时性的
Well, it's only temporary, you know.
不是那个问题
It's not that.
那是什么问题?
What's the problem?
你不喜欢我?
You don't like me?
你不喜欢龟仔?  是什么问题?
You don't like the turtles? What's the problem?
-我觉得我不属于这里  -不要紧
-I don't think I belong here.  -It's okay.
我不属于这里
I don't belong here.
不要紧  因为你是我客人
Well, you know, it's okay, 'cause you're my guest.
我认识你不够深  我未试过单独在男人住所
I don't... know you well enough. I've never been in a man's apartment alone.
都是一样的
Well, I... they're all the same. You know.
我认识你不够深
I'm not sure I know you well enough.
我觉得不自在
I don't feel comfortable.
我也不十分自在
Yo, Adrian, you know, I ain't so comfortable either.
我该走了
I should go.
不要走  求你  不要走
Don't go, please. Don't go. Don't go. Don't go.
不要走
Don't go.
帮我一个忙
Do me a favor?
是什么?
What?
摘下眼镜
Take off these glasses.
你眼睛很漂亮  知道吗?
You have nice eyes.
多帮我一个忙?
Do me another favor?
摘下帽子
Would you take off that hat?
我一直知道你很漂亮
I always knew you was pretty.
-不要取笑我  -我不是取笑你
-Don't tease me.  -I'm not teasing you.
我不是取笑你
I ain't teasin' ya.
我只是想...吻你
I just...wanna kiss you.
你不需要回吻我  如果你不想的话
You don't have to kiss me back if you don't want.
但我想吻你
But I wanna kiss you.
斡姆  听说你就快有拳赛
Worm, I heard you had a fight comin' up.
下个月有
Yeah, I'm gonna fight next month.
那很好  你来拳击馆  我们来看你
That's good, man. You come down to the gym, we'll see that you get in shape.
-你多重?  -175  -洛奇  你好吗?
-How's your weight? -I weigh 175. -Hey, Rock. How you doin', babe?
-嘿  -米克正在上面找你
-Hey. -Oh, Mick was lookin' for you up there.
-找我?  -是
-For me? -Yeah.
-你肯定?  -是
-You sure?  -Yeah, yeah, yeah.
他在找你 快上去找他
He was lookin' for you,Jack.Get on up there and see him.
是 你叫洛奇 是吗
Yeah.It ain't locked,right?
-是  -对了  快去
-Yeah, yeah.  -All right, go on, man.
你找我?
Hey, you got somethin' for me?
米路·休根斯那边有个人来找你
Yeah, there was some guy here from Miles Jergens lookin' for you.
他们要替阿波罗·奎迪找练拳对手
They need sparring partners for Apollo Creed.
-你就让我去啊  -名片在这里
-You're puttin' me on.  -There's the card.
-他何时来的?  -大概一小时前
-When was he here?  -About an hour ago.
他们可能要替奎迪找练拳对手
They're probably lookin' for sparrin' partners for Creed, you know?
我不是刚说了吗  笨蛋
I said that before, you dumb dago!
我在这里六年了 六年来你一直跟我过不去
I've been comin' here for six years, and six years you been stickin' it to me.
为什么?
I wanna know how come.
你不会想知道
You don't wanna know.
-我想知道  -你想知道?  -我想知道!
-Yeah, I wanna know how come. -You wanna know? -I wanna know!
好  我告诉你
Okay, I'm gonna tell ya!
你有天份成为出色拳手
'Cause you had the talent to become a good fighter,
但你却去帮二流高利贷打人收帐
and instead of that, you became a leg-breaker to some cheap, second-rate loan shark.
只是生活而已
It's a livin'.
是浪费生命
It's a waste of life!
有何贵干?
Yes, may I help you?
你一定是洛奇·巴尔博亚 休根斯先生在等你  请稍等
Oh! You must be Mr. Rocky Balboa. Mr. Jergens is expecting you. Just a moment.
洛奇·巴尔博亚先生来了
Mr. Rocky Balboa to see you, sir.
好
Fine.
-请进去  -那个可否给我?
-Will you please go in, Mr. Balboa.  -Can I have that?
-当然可以  -谢谢
-Oh, certainly.  -Thanks.
巴尔博亚先生
Mr. Balboa.
你好吗?  我是佐治·休根斯
How are you? George Jergens.
请坐
Take a chair, please.
谢谢
Thanks.
巴尔博亚先生
Mr. Balboa.
-叫我洛奇吧  -洛奇
-Call me Rocky.  -Rocky.
有人代表你吗?
Tell me, Rocky, you got any representation?
有经理人吗?
You have a manager?
-没有  就我自己  -哦
-No. It's just me.  -Oh.
洛奇  我有一项建议想向你提出
Rocky, I've got a proposition I'd like to make to you.
-关于做练拳对手?  -什么?
-Uh, sparrin'?  -Beg your pardon?
我知你在找练拳对手
Well, it's just I know you're lookin' for sparrin' partners,
我可以做
and I just wanna say I'm very available, you know.
我肯定你可以
I'm sure you are.
是的  跟拳王练拳是我的光荣
Absolutely. Sparrin' with the Champ would be an honor.
-而且还有  -是什么?
-And you know what, Mr. Jergens?  -What?
我不会出暗拳  我是很好的练拳对手
I wouldn't take no cheap shots, either. I'd really be a good sparring partner.
你搞错了  洛奇
You don't understand me, Rocky.
我的建议是...
My proposition is this...
你会否有兴趣跟阿波罗·奎迪
Would you be interested in fighting Apollo Creed
在世界重量级拳王赛上决战?
for the World Heavyweight Championship?
不会
No.
听着  洛奇
Listen, Rocky...
阿波罗看过你比赛
Apollo's seen you fight.
他喜欢你  他想跟你打
He likes you. He wants to fight you.
只是  你要明白
Well, it's just that, you see, uh...
我平时只在拳馆打  我不能赢大赛
I fight in clubs, you know. I'm really a ham-and-egger.
他是拳王...那不会是精彩拳赛
This guy...he's the best, and, uh, it wouldn't be such a good fight.
但谢谢你们好意
But thank you very much, you know.
我十分感激
I appreciate it and all that.
洛奇  你相信美国遍地机会吗?
Rocky? Do you believe that America is the land of opportunity?
相信
Yeah.
阿波罗·奎迪也相信
Apollo Creed does.
他会证明给全世界看
And he's gonna prove it to the whole world
就是让一个无名之辈 有争冠军的机会
by giving an unknown a shot at the title.
而那无名之辈就是你
And that unknown is you.
他选了你  洛奇
He picked you, Rocky.
这是毕生难逢的机遇
Rocky, it's the chance of a lifetime.
你不能错过
You can't pass it by.
你意下如何?
What do you say?
好了  不要拍照了
All right, fellas, fellas. That's enough pictures.
我们想问阿波罗几个问题
We wanna ask Apollo a few questions.
阿波罗  你对费城感觉如何?
Apollo, how do you like the city of brotherly love?
身在费城令我充满爱国情绪
Well, just being in Philadelphia makes me feel patriotic.
美丽城市里的美丽人民
Beautiful people in a beautiful city
在街上走来  祝福我
comin' up to me on the street wishing me the best.
我爱我费城的兄弟  而我因身为美国人而骄傲
I love my Philadelphia brothers, and I'm proud to be an American.
阿波罗?  拳王?  你为什么同意
Champ, Apollo, why did you agree to fight a man
跟一个毫无胜出机会的人决斗?
who has virtually no chance of winning?
历史已证实了
Look, if history proves one thing,
美国历史证实了任何人都有机会赢
American history proves that everybody's got a chance to win.
你们没听过霍谷或賓架山吗?
Didn't you guys ever hear of Valley Forge or Bunker Hill?
-阿波罗?  -恩?
-Apollo, Apollo, Apollo.  -Yes?
你在本国史上最重要的节庆日 跟一个白人决战
It is a coincidence that you're fighting a white man
是纯粹巧合吗?
on the most celebrated day in the country's history?
我不知道
I don't know about that.
在本国史上最重要的节庆日
Is it a coincidence that he's fighting
跟一个黑人决战又是巧合吗
a black man on the most celebrated day in the country's history?
说得好  阿波罗!  说真相  兄弟
Right on! Tell the truth, brother!
阿波罗  你觉得你的挑战者如何?
Listen, Apollo, tell me... how do you feel about your challenger?
-我觉得他如何?  -是的
-How do I feel about him?  -Yeah.
你什么意思?  过来  洛奇
What do you mean? Come here, Rock.
我的对手  洛奇  你是意大利人吗?
My main man, Rocky, ain't you Italian?
是  我是意大利人
Yeah, I'm Italian.
你问了干吗?
Well, now, what does that mean?
就算他不打得  都赌得
It means if he can't fight, I bet he can cook.
好的
All right, Rocky.
帮个忙  打穿他个肺...
Do me a favor. His lungs... punch 'em out.
保利
Paulie.
你打算怎样打阿波罗·奎迪?
But, Rocky, how do you expect to fight Apollo Creed?
噢  奎迪是最出色的
Uh, well, geez, you know. Creed's the best.
我只有尽力而为
I guess I'll have to do the best I can.
告诉我  洛奇  就我们两个...
Tell me, Rocky, just between us...
你那意大利牡马的称号 是怎样来的?
where did you get the name "Italian Stallion"?
是我八年前
Oh... uh, I invented that about eight years ago
吃晚餐时想到的  洛奇  你对于会得到十五万元报酬
when I was eatin' dinner. Rocky, now your payday will be $150.000.
有什么意见?
Any comment?
你没有意见  对吗  洛奇?   没有意见
You... you got no comment, Rocky, right? No comment.
谢谢  洛奇
Right. Thank you, Rocky.
慢着  我想跟我女朋友打招呼  可以吗?
Wait a minute. I just wanna say hi to my girlfriend, okay?
-我...  -艾莉  是我  洛奇
-I, uh... -Yo, Adrian! It's me, Rocky.
你相信吗?  很多麦克风和记者
Look at this. Can you believe all this? They put a microphone on me.
-你不是吧  -谢谢  洛奇
-You didn't.  -Thank you, Rocky.
-你推什么?  -谢谢  洛奇
-Quit pushin', man!  -Thank you, Rocky.
他令你变傻仔  你不介意?  是我就打爆他的嘴
Don't it matter he's makin' you out a fool? I'd break his lips.
-他在出暗拳  -我不介意
-He's taking cheap shots.  -It don't bother me none.
洛奇  你要找人帮你
Yo, Rock...I guess you'll be looking for people to help you out.
-帮什么?  -帮你过正常生活
-Help in what?  -Keep you livin' the clean life.
我生活得很好  你知道
I'll do okay. You know.
你需要人帮你练习
You need someone to help with the exercise,
递毛巾  做跑腿?
and someone standing by with a towel, or runnin' errands. You know.
之前有谁关心我?  没有人
Hey, yo, Paulie, who cared about me yesterday, huh? Nobody.
所以我会自己锻炼
So I just think I'm gonna train myself, you know.
没有那些专业人员帮你
Without such good people around to help,
你机会很小
you don't have such a good chance.
爱恩斯坦被逐出校两次
Einstein flunked out of school twice.
是吗?
That so?
是
Yeah.
贝多芬是聋的  海伦·凯勒是盲的
Beethoven was deaf. Helen Keller was blind.
我觉得洛奇机会不错
I think Rocky's got a good chance.
保利  要我帮你拿啤酒吗?
Want me to get you a beer, Paulie?
你想帮我?  离开我的生活
Hey, you lookin' to do a good deed? Keep out of my freakin' life!
-我做错了什么?  -没有
-What'd I do?  -Nothin'.
-我说错了话吗?  -你没说什么  不要紧
-What? Did I say something wrong?  -You didn't say nothin'. It's all right.
对了...  你没说什么 什么都没说
That's right... you didn't say nothin'! Nothin' at all!
-我走先  -哦
-I gotta go.  -Oh.
椒盐脆饼在哪里?
Where's the freakin' pretzels?!
我想吃椒盐脆饼  喂  我们没啤酒?
I got the pretzels! Hey! We ain't got any beer?
我以为你会去买啤酒
I thought you were supposed to pick up some beer.
今晚在电视上听到自己名字 觉得怎样?
How'd you like hearing your name on TV tonight?
我很震惊  你干吗那样做?
I was shocked. Why'd you do that?
你跟我开玩笑  是吗?
Come on. You're puttin' me on, right?
当然是
Absolutely.
你什么时候来?
What time should I expect you?
大约7点  好的   嘿
Oh, about 7:00. Hey.
你记得我之前说 电视上发生的事我不介意吗?
You know how I said that stuff on TV didn't bother me none?
记得
Yeah.
其实我介意
It did.
我带你来  是因为
Listen, the reason I brought you here is because, uh...
我想知道你有训练用的资金吗
I wanna know if you got any money for training expenses, eh?
我有几元
I got a few dollars.
几元?  这里  放进拳套里
A few bucks? Well, here. Put this in your glove.
-是什么?  -500元  不用担心
-What's this?  -500 bucks. Don't worry about it.
你从来没有运气
You know, you ain't never had any luck,
但这次你可能有女人运  你觉得呢?
but I think this time Lady Luck may be in your corner. What do you think?
可能吧
Maybe. Maybe.
谢谢你的钱  汤尼
Hey, thanks for the money, Tony, you know.
不用客气  迟些见
It's okay. Don't worry about it. See ya, all right?
-慢着  -什么事?
-Hey, wait a minute.  -What?
你现在要训练  不要抽烟
You're in training, huh? Come on.
嘿
Hey.
-汤尼  -怎样?
-Yo, Tony.  -What?
你会去看那场拳赛吗?
You gonna show up at the fight?
我会到擂台边
Ringside.
好额  再见
Hey, ey.
再见
I'll see ya.
来了
Yeah?
你好  我见你还开着灯 可以进来吗?
Hello, kid. I seen your light. Can I come in?
-当然可以  -好
-Yeah, sure.  -Yeah, good.
地方很不错
Hey, it's a nice place here.
我是来告诉你
All right, anyway, what I come to tell you is that, uh...
你的际遇完全是运气
that what happened to you is freak luck.
-是  运气  -不是吗?  看其他人
-Yeah, freak luck.  -Ain't it true? Look at the other guys.
他们是出色拳手  他们打得精彩  成绩好
Now, they're good fighters, right? They're colorful, they got good records.
他们为了少少钱搏命
They fight their guts out for peanuts.
但你居然有机会争拳王宝座
But you... you get a shot at the title.
运气真是奇怪的东西
Freak luck is a strange thing.
的确是  我可以坐下吗?
Yeah, sure it is. Can I sit down?
当然可以
Yeah, sure.
那些是什么?
What the hell are those?
家龟
Oh, those are domestic turtles.
上面那隻是袖口  另外那隻是链扣
The one on the top is Cuff and the other guy's Link.
其余的是石粒
The rest of them are marbles.
是吗?  可以拿来煲靓汤
Yeah? They make good soup, don't they?
言归正传  我是来忠告你的
Anyway, look... I'm here to warn ya
你要好小心处理这次争宝座的机会
that you gotta be very careful about this shot that you got at the title,
因为  正如圣经上说
because, I don't know, like the Bible says...
你不会有第二次机会
you ain't gonna get a second chance.
是  好的
Yeah. All right.
你有想过吗?
You thought of that, huh?
你需要一个经理人
Well, what you need is a manager.
经理人  听我说
A manager. Listen to me.
我知道  因为我在这行打滚了50年
I know because I've been in this racket for 50 years.
-50年  -50年
-50 years, huh? -50 years.
-我什么都见过  你知我做过什么吗?  -什么?
-God, I've seen it all. All of it. You know what I done? -What?
我什么都做过
I have done it all.
你应该看我把鸡仔·罗素打到跌出擂台
You shoulda seen me when I knocked Giny Russo outta the ring.
跌出擂台  那是1923年9月14日
Outta the goddamn ring. That's, uh, September the 14th, 1923.
那一晚也是科普把登斯 打下擂台的一晚
And it was the same night that Firpo knocks Dempsey outta the ring.
结果是谁得到传媒报导?
The same night. So, who gets the publicity? Figure that out.
-登斯  -对了  但为什么?
-Dempsey.  -That's right. But why?
-因为他是拳王  -不 因为他有经理人
-'Cause he was Champ.  -No! Because he had a manager.
我什么也没有
I had nothin', man.
我给你看一样东西  看我的脸
I wanna show you somethin'. Look at my face for a minute.
看这个  左眼上面缝了21针
Look at this. I got 21 stitches over this left eye.
这隻眼有34针
I got 34 stitches over this eye.
我鼻子被人打爆过17次
You know what? I had my nose busted 17 times.
最后一次是在跟舍勒米克决战时 被打爆的
The last time was with that fight with Sailor Mike.
我还保留着那报导  很精彩的拳赛
I got that clip in here. That was a good fight.
要看吗?
You wanna read that?
没关系了
You... oh, it doesn't matter.
总之他打到我双耳变形
Anyway, he put this vegetation on my ear.
洛奇·马西安诺  世界重量级拳击冠军
Ah, Rocky Marciano.
你令我想起那洛奇  知吗?
You know, you kinda remind me of the Rock, you know that?
真的?
You really think so?
是  你的动作像他  而且有他一样的 斗心
That's right. You move like him, and you got heart like he did.
我有 斗心  但我没有储物柜
Yeah, I got heart, but I ain't got no locker, do I, Mick?
怎样都好
Uh... anyway,
我刚入这行时...
you know, when I begun in this business, kid...
我建议你比赛前不要喝酒
Look, kid, I wanna make a suggestion. Don't drink that piss before a fight.
对你无益
You know, it's no good for you.
希望你不介意我这样说
If you don't mind my sayin'.
我刚入这行时
Anyway, you know, when I started this racket,
我们这些拳手都被人当狗
pugs like us, we was treated like dogs.
为了10元  你要扯断别人喉咙
For ten bucks, you gotta tear somebody's throat out.
但我从来没有经理人
But I never had no management. You know...
有一次... 这个人渣
One time, this... this son of a bitch that I fought,
他在那里放了粒钉
he put a nail right there.
-在姆指  -在拳套姆指上
-Thumb. -The thumb, yeah. In the glove.
他在我脸上钉了很多个洞
And he punched so many holes in my face.
口水都从脸颊喷出来
I had the spit shootin' out of my cheeks.
你可以想像吗?
Can you imagine that?
让我告诉你我全盛时期的样子
Anyway, I'll tell ya what I looked like when I was, uh, in my prime.
你看这个   看这个
I want you to look at some... will you look at that? Look at that.
那是我被那些人  打残以前的样子
That's the way I looked... before these guys got at me.
很不错 这照片你保存的很好
That's nice. You take very good care of the picture, though.
我从来没人管理
But I never had...
那正是问题
I never had no management... that's the trouble!
但我现在有知识和经验  都在脑子里  我想传授给你
But now I got all this knowledge. I got it up here.  Now I wanna give it to you!
我想把那知识传授给你  我想照顾你
I wanna give you this knowledge. I wanna take care of you.
确保你不用行我的旧路
I wanna make sure that all this shit that happened to me doesn't happen to you.
你明我意思吗?
You know what I mean?
-那场赛事已经定下  -我想做你经理人
-The fight's set. -Listen to me. I wanna be your manager.
-你明白吧?  -赛事已定下  我不需要经理人
-You follow that, do you?  -The fight's set. I don't need a manager.
但我能给你的  是你不能用钱买的
But you can't buy what I'm gonna give you.
我有痛苦和经历
I mean, I've got pain and I've got experience.
我也有痛苦和经历
Well, I got pain and I got experience, too.
孩子  听着
Listen, kid...
-米克  -什么?
-Hey, yo. Hey, Mick. -What?
我十年前需要你
I needed your help about ten years ago, right? Ten years ago?
-是的  -十年前  你从没帮过我  你不关心
-Right. -You never helped me. You didn't care.
你需要帮忙...
Well, if you wanted help...
你需要帮忙  干吗不问我?
I say, if you wanted help, why didn't you ask?
你干吗不那样问我  孩子?
Why didn't you just ask me, kid?
我问过你  但你没听见
Look, I asked, but you never heard nothin'!
我...
Well, I...
I, uh...
我知我...我76岁了
I know I...I'm 76 years old.
而且...
And, uh... well.
他妈的在哪里...
Where the hell is...
那么久才来这里
Took you long enough to get here.
过了十年才来我家
Took you ten years to come to my house?
你不喜欢我的家吗?
Huh, what's the matter? You don't like my house?
我的家发臭?
Does my house stink?
对了  是很臭
That's right... it stinks!
我没受过你恩惠
I didn't have no favors from you!
不要这样没礼貌对我!
Don't slum around me!
还在说全盛时期
Talkin' about your prime.
那我的全盛时期呢  米克?
What about my prime, Mick?!
至少你有过全盛时期
At least you had a prime!
我没有全盛时期  我什么都没有
I didn't have no prime. I didn't have nothin'!
双腿不行了  一切都不行了 没人给过我什么
Leg's are goin', everything is goin', Nobody's gettin' no nothin'.
有人来叫我打场拳赛  有什么大不了
Guy comes up, offers me a fight. Big deal.
想打那场拳赛吗?  好  我去打那场大赛
Wanna fight the fight? Yeah, I'll fight the big fight.
我会去打那场大赛  而且会赢
I wouldn't wanna fight. Know what's gonna happen to me? I'm gonna get that!
我会赢
I'm gonna get that!
你要到擂台边看吗?
And you wanna be ringside to see it?
要吗?  想帮我?
Do ya? You wanna help me out?
你想看我被人打扁脸吗?
Huh? Do you wanna see me get my face kicked in?!
双腿不行  什么都不行
Legs ain't workin', nothing's workin',
以为我会去跟拳王决斗
but they go. "Go on, fight the champ."
是  我会跟他打
Yeah, I'll fight him.
被人打扁脸
Get my face kicked in.
你还走来这里  想搬进来吗?
And you come around here. You wanna move in here with me?!
来呀  这间屋很不错
Come on in! It's a nice house!
很不错 进来呀 臭的
Real nice. Come on in and move. It stinks!
整间屋发臭
This whole place stinks.
你想帮我?
You wanna help me out? Well, help me out!
来  帮我呀  我在这里
Come on, help me out. I'm standin' here!
气温只有零下2度  我们看天气预测
It's only about 28 degrees. We'll check that forecast in just a minute.
我觉得是恶作剧  很奇怪...
I feel very mischievous. Very weird. Very...
我车上的是胶椅
Well, the thing is, I got vinyl seats in my car.
我今早坐上架车  大叫"呜"
When I hit the seats this morning, I just went. "Whew!"
如果我都起了床
I'm thinkin', if I'm up,
德拉威谷的人都应该起了床  你同意吗?
everybody in the Delaware Valley should be up. Do you agree with me?
早上4点零3分  你还会做什么?
I mean, at three minutes past 4:00, what else are you gonna do?
-喂?  -早晨  桂玛太太
-Hello?  -Good morning, Mrs. Kramer.
我是费城电台的东·卡能
This is Don Cannon, W-I-B-G Philadelphia.
-你今早好吗?  -什么?
-How are you this morning? -Huh?
-桂玛太太?  -什么?
-Mrs. Kramer?  -What?!
你居然够胆那么早打来!  再见
I think you have a lot of nerve calling me at this hour in the morning! Goodbye!
W-I-B-G
费城
Philadelphia
我和桂玛太太都起了床 这是很好的早上
Me and Mrs. Kramer are up, and it's a good morning.
零下2度  我需要人来拥抱  外面很冷
I tell ya, I need someone to snuggle with, 28 degrees. It's cold out there.
是报应  我们上两星期逃脱了谋杀罪
We deserve it. We've been getting away with murder the last couple weeks.
今日最高气温是...
Our high today could possibly be 58, and that's it.
今晚我们会回到零下温度
Tonight we're back down on the 20 degree range,
近郊再冷一点  明天幸运的话
a little colder in the suburbs, and tomorrow, with a little bit of luck,
可上到4度
we may hit 40 somewhere.
但现在是零下2度  很冷
But it's 28, it's awfully chilly.
出门前记得保暖
Make sure you have it snuggled on before you bring it out.
费城肉品包装协会成员
有没有搞错
Come on.
这里很臭  你知吗?
Stinks in... hey, come on. It stinks in here, you know.
是  我知道
Yeah... I know.
全部都是你屠宰的?
Hey, did you kill all these things?
不  是在对面街屠宰的
No. Across the street.
这里像动物殓房
This place is like an animal morgue, you know?
-太冷了  -是
-It's a little cold in here, ain't it?  -Yeah.
谁屠宰的?
Who killed all these things?
你疯了吗  保利?
What, are you crazy, Paulie?
你不付钱给加索  就要上吊
If you don't pay Gazzo, you end up on the hook.
加索是好人  你知道的
Come on, Gazzo's a good man. You know that.
不要激动  我知道
Hey, don't get excited. I know that.
所以我才要你跟他谈 请我做收帐的事
That's why I want you to talk to him about me...the collectin' job.
带我离开这臭冰柜
Get me out of this stinkin' freezer.
不如你当帮自己
Why don't you do yourself a favor?
继续做这份工 那样吃得较好
Why don't you keep this job, because you eat better, you know?
这里会下雪的吗?
Does it ever snow in here?
你跟我妹妹
Uh... you and my sister.
进展如何?
How you gettin' along together?
你认为呢?
How do you think?
我不肯定  洛奇  实情是怎样?
Well, I'm not sure, Rock. What's the story?
关于什么?
About what?
你们之间所发生的
What's the story? What's happening?
你真的喜欢她?
Do you really like her?
我当然喜欢她
Sure, I like her.
我不明白  她有什么吸引你?
I don't see it. What's the attraction?
我不知道  大概是互补不足
I don't know. It fills gaps, I guess.
-什么不足 ?  -我不知道  我和她都有不足之处
-What's gaps?  -I don't know. Gaps. She's got gaps, I got gaps.
一起便能互补不足
Together, we fill gaps. I don't know.
你跟她上过床吗?
You ballin' her?
你不能用诬秽的话来说你妹妹
Hey, you don't talk dirty about your sister.
你有跟她上床吗?
Are you screwin' my sister?
你明白吗?  我为什么不介绍你给加索
You see? That's why I can't connect you with Gazzo, you know that, Paulie?
因为你是大嘴巴  你太多话
Because you got a big mouth, you know. You just talk too much.
这里很冷  我要回家了
It's gettin' cold in here. I'm going home.
这里冷?  这里是很冷
Cold in here?! It is cold in here!
这里很臭  你很臭
It stinks in here, and you stink!
你打断了肋骨
Hey, you're breakin' the ribs.
如果你那样打阿波罗·奎迪 我们会被拉去坐牢
If you do that to Apollo Creed, they'll put us in jail for murder.
明早见
I'll see ya tomorrow morning, okay?
-我调高了暖气  -谢谢
-I turned the heat up. -Thanks.
你哥哥是好人  只是太固执
You know, your brother's a good man, but he's awful pushy, you know?
-你要我帮你擦吗?  -不用  我只是酸痛
-You want me to rub you down? -No, I'm just... I'm just sore, okay?
我坐着就可以
I'll just... just sit here.
-真的?  -真的
-You sure?  -Yeah, I'm sure.
不要  不能上床  知吗?
Hey, come on. No foolin' around, all right?
我很累
I'm tired.
艾莉  我现在是认真的
Hey, Adrian, I'm serious now.
训练期间不能上床  我要养精蓄锐
There's no foolin' around during training, understand? I wanna stay strong.
-你不是说笑 -不  我不是说笑
-You're not kiddin'? -No, I ain't kiddin'.
-你肯定?  -是  我肯定
-You sure?  -Yeah, I'm sure.
不如你去煮肉吧?
Listen, why don't you just make the meat, okay?
好  我去煮肉
Okay, I'll make the meat.
-不要紧  -对不起
-It's okay.  -I'm sorry.
嘿
Hey.
右边  右边  左边  左边
Right, right. Left, left.
下边  加油  下边
Underneath. Come on, underneath.
下面  下面  击倒他
Underneath, underneath, underneath. Come on!
等等  洛奇
Hold it. Hold it.
我真是要发疯了
Hold it, Rock, will ya? You drive me crazy.
你打得那样无力 因为你失了平衡
You're so sloppy because you're off balance.
试这个  拿这条绳  绑着两边足踝
Let's try this. Now, take this string. Tie it to both ankles.
留两尺空位
Leave about two feet of slack.
我步法一向不好
I ain't never had good footwork.
不用理步法  现在你平衡了
Never mind footwork. Now you're all balanced.
马西安诺也有同样问题  这条绳医好了他
Marciano had the same problem, and this string cured it.
如果...
Here's the idea...
你能走动和出拳 而不弄断条绳
that if you can move and you can hit without breaking the string,
你就取得平衡了
you got balance.
你就变成危险人物
You become a very dangerous person.
-明白吗? -打得不错  洛奇  -谢谢 -继续
-You follow? -You're lookin' good, Rock.  -Thanks. -Let's go.
对了  是这样的  是这样的  下面
That's it. That's it. Underneath.
-嘿  洛奇    -什么事?
-Hey, Rock.  -What?
-签个名好吗?  -走开!
-How 'bout you give us your autograph?  -Get outta here!
我在做生意  不要骚扰我
Don't you ever interrupt me while I'm conducting business.
快出去
Move your little chicken asses out of here.
你暂时不要碰那宠物店女孩
Listen, kid. You! You lay off that pet shop dame.
女人令人脚软
Women weaken legs.
是  但我真的很喜欢她
Yeah, but I really like this girl, you know?
那叫她来训练你
Then let her train ya!
-好的  我不碰她  -好  出拳
-Okay, no more foolin' around. -Okay. Now hit it.
女人令人脚软  是吗?
Women weaken legs, huh?
-洛奇  -洛奇
-Yo, Rock.  -Yo, Rocky.
你很好看
Yo, you look great.
-真的?  -是呀
-Really?  -Oh, yeah.
很漂亮  你会令人心碎
Terrific. I mean, you could be a heartbreaker.
你这样走到街上会有男人为你心碎
You'll walk down the street breaking hearts,
很抢镜
the way you're lookin'...very sharp.
还有一个惊喜给你
I got...I got another surprise for you.
是什么?
What?
毕寇斯   过来
Hey, Butkus! Hey, Butkus! Come here, kid! Come here!
在你跑步时给你做个伴
To keep you company when you run.
快进来见其他家庭成员  歌莉亚没回来吗
Come on in and meet the family. The owner ever come back?
-歌莉亚说  你要的话就给你  -我要不要它?
-He's yours. He's yours if you want him. -Do I want him? Come here!
它吃什么...  这只狗?
What's he eat... this dog?
-它吃小龟  -毕寇斯
-He eats little turtles. -Yo, Butkus!
怎么了  毕寇斯?  是谁的货车?  来
What's that, Butkus, huh? Whose truck is this? Come on.
我打个电话  你就做了名人
One call from me, you're a celebrity.
-你需要曝光率  -不要对着我喷气
-You're gonna need exposure. -Oh, don't breathe on me, Paulie!
可以帮你出名  你以为我不懂吗?
That's the big time! Don't I know about these things?
你懂个屁  他们想我怎样?
You don't know nothin'! What do these guys want from me?
看着你受训
To watch you train! Boom.
你有病吗?  这是很私人的
What is the matter with you, Paulie? This was supposed to be private.
-我在帮你  -你不是在帮我
-I'm doin' you a favor!  -You ain't doin' me no favors!
你令我在人前出丑
You're embarrassin' me in front of everybody,
你令我在你妹妹面前丢脸...
you make me look bad in front of your sister...
我会把这支雪茄塞进你耳朵 不要对我做这些东西
You see this cigar? I'll stick it in your ear. Don't do these things to me!
你应该先通知我... 留个口讯
You should've called me up or something... leave a message.
不能这样
Don't do that!
我妹妹真的很喜欢你
My sister really likes you.
我迟早杀了你
I'm gonna kill you one of these days, I swear to God!
来
Come on. Come on.
-宝贝  -宝贝
-Baby!  -Baby.
这就是 即将接任的世界重量级拳王  洛奇·巴尔博亚
Here he is, the next heavyweight champ, Rocky Balboa!
你好  洛奇·巴尔博亚
Hi, there. Rocky Balboa.
我们想访问你  不会耽误你很久的
Listen, we wanna get a brief interview with you. It won't take long.
-我呢?  -你怎样?
-What about me?  -What about you?
-我负责管肉类  -好  站在后面
-I'm in charge of the meat. -Fine. Will you stand behind it, please?
你不要紧张   放松
Listen, just settle yourself in. Just relax.
我们会问你几个问题
What we're going to do is just ask you a few questions, Rocky.
只是几个问题  关于你独特的训练方法
Just a few questions about your unique training method.
跟观众说几句
Talk to the folks at home.
他们想知道你是怎样想到这方法的
They really wanna know how you got into this.
这不是日常见到的
I mean, this isn't an everyday thing.
杰美  准备好了吗?  开始摄影
Jimmy, you guys ready? Let's roll.
洛奇  在这里转身
Rocky, why don't you turn right around here.
不要拍得我像傻仔
Just don't take no cheap shots, you know?
我不会的  放松点
No, I won't do that. Just relax, Rocky.
今天我们来到访问 重量级挑战者洛奇·巴尔博亚
Today we're here with heavyweight challenger Rocky Balboa.
-我们来到这个...  -那冻肉佬伸了头进来
-The reason we're standing... -The meat guy's stickin' his face in.
我们再来过
Let's try it again, Rocky.
今天我们来到访问  重量级挑战者洛奇·巴尔博亚
Today we're here with heavyweight challenger Rocky Balboa.
我们来到这个冷藏库
The reason we're standing in this refrigerated box
是因为巴尔博亚先生有一套特别的训练方法
is that Mr. Balboa has an unusual method of training.
过一会他会
In a moment, he's going to demonstrate that
向大家示范
for the viewing audience at home.
但首先要问洛奇 你怎么会来到冷藏库训练的?
But first, Rocky, how did you come to train in an icebox?
是我的朋友...那边那个人...
Uh, well, my friend... the guy over there...
有天他让我进来 我打了这里的牛肉  发觉很好
let me in one day and I hit the beef here and kinda liked it.
因为我是挑战者 这里的老板也不介意我来训练
And since I become a challenger, the owner don't mind that I come in.
这训练方法普遍吗?  其他拳手会打生肉吗?
Is this a common training method? Do other fighters pound raw meat?
不  是我发明的
No, I think I invented it.
订好擂台边的座位  给我的人
Don't forget to confirm the reservation for my people at ringside,
和让我的发型师飞来费城
and be sure to fly my barber to Philly.
给了西岸闭路广告多少钱?
How much is being channeled into West Coast closed circuit advertising?
-三十万   -加到四十五万
-$300,000.  -Make it 450.
以我名义送二百支玫瑰给市长夫人
And send the mayor's wife 200 roses from me,
记着要拍照片给报馆
and make sure we get a picture of it for all the newspapers.
你要中西部那十五个电台的广告时段吗?
Do you wanna run the 15 radio spots in the Midwest?
那些钱放在加拿大做宣传更好
I think you could spend your money better in Canadian publicity.
对了...阿波罗 我在多伦多有些朋友
By the way...I've got a couple of friends up in Toronto
可以给你税务优惠
who'd probably be able to get you a good tax break.
佐治  我喜欢你的朋友
George, I like your friends.
拳王
Hey, Champ...
快过来看  你的对手上电视了
you oughta come look at this boy you're gonna fight on TV.
看来他很认真
Looks like he means business.
我也很认真
Yeah, I mean business, too.
雪莉  出面还有咖啡吗?
Shirley, we got any more coffee out there?
当然有  奎迪先生  我立即去拿
Oh, certainly, Mr. Creed. I'll get you some right away.
拳赛之后  或者我会退休 竞选做皇帝
After the fight, I may just retire and run for emperor.
那个地域唯一的节目
The arena's the only program concession,
将要包括400...
and the gross rental of the arena is gonna include the 400 ushers, right?
戴安娜·路易丝在冻肉场 跟南泽西洛奇·巴尔博亚的访问完毕
Diana Lewis, in the meat house with southpaw Rocky Balboa.
他找了记者来?
And he called the reporters?
是  打乱了我的训练时间
Yeah, it threw my whole training schedule off.
不要恼他  他只是想帮忙
Don't be mad at him. He's just trying to help.
我没恼他
Adrian, I ain't mad, it's just that, uh,
只是有记者令我乱了阵脚
when a reporter's around, I get out of joint
因为他们会把我拍得很差  保利知道的
'cause they take cheap shots, and Paulie knows that.
保利不停叫我介绍工作
Paulie keeps askin' me for a job all the time,
但他对打架一窍不通
but he don't know nothin' about fightin'.
你会跟他说吗?
Are you gonna say anything to him?
说什么?  我不知道他想从我身上得到什么
What's to say? I just don't know what he wants from me.
我不要从你身上得到什么
I don't want nothin' from you.
这不是施舍
This ain't no charity case.
滚出我间屋
Get outta my house.
这间屋不是你一个人的
It's not just your house.
你不再是我朋友
You ain't no friend no more.
-滚出我间屋  我刚说了 -不要那样对他说话
-Get out of my house, I just says. -Don't talk to him like that.
你两个都滚出我间屋
Both of you get out of my house.
外面很冷  保利
It's cold outside, Paulie.
我不准你再搞她
I don't want you messin' her,
我养大你不是要你跟这人渣一起
and I don't raise you to go with this scum bum!
来啊  你想打我吗?
Come on! Wanna hit on me? Come on!
来 我会打断你双臂 等你不能再打拳
I'll break both your arms so they don't work for ya!
停手   我不够资格去见加索?
That's right! I'm not good enough to meet with Gazzo...
加索算什么
That's what I think of Gazzo!
现在你做了大人物
Now you're a big-shot fighter on your way up,
也不帮朋友
you don't even throw a crumb to your friend Paulie!
枉我每朝拿冻肉给你
When I go and get you meat every morning!
你忘了?  我还把妹妹给你
You forgot that! Then I even give you my sister, too!
-你没有人性才会说这样的话  -我没有人性?
-Only a pig would say that! -I'm a pig?
我没有人性会把最好的给你?
A pig gives you the best?
你这个没有用的人  我没结婚也是因为你
You're such a loser! I don't get married because of you!
你不能自己住
You can't live by yourself!
是我撮合你两个  你不要忘记
I put you two together! And you... don't you forget it!
是你欠我的
You owe me!
-你欠我  -我欠你什么?
-You owe me!  -What do I owe you?!
你应该要好好对我
You're supposed to be good to me.
我欠你什么  保利?
What do I owe you, Paulie?! What do I owe ya?!
我对你很好
I treat you good!
我为你煮饭  清洁  洗衣服
I cook for you, I clean for you, I pick up your dirty clothes!
我一直照顾你  我没欠你什么
I take care of you, Paulie! I don't owe you nothin'!
但你令我觉得自己没有用
And you made me feel like a loser!
我不是没有用
I'm not a loser!
-你失了贞操  -什么?
-You're busted!  -What?!
你不是处女
You're not a virgin!
你让一个男人脱掉你裤子  她失了贞操
You let him into your pants! She's busted!
我不想再搬冻肉
I can't haul meat no more!
你想我搬到你那吗?
You want a roommate?
当然
Absolutely.
当你走上擂台
Okay, now, when you walk into the ring
面对世界第一的重量级拳手
with the number one heavyweight of the world,
你会准备好
you'll be ready, won't ya?
为什么?  因为我等了50年  去令你准备好
Why? Because I waited for 50 years to make you ready.
你将会超级强劲   像他们说的  你可以吃闪电
You'll be able to spit nails, kid. Like the guy says, you're gonna eat lightning
放雷屁
and you're gonna crap thunder.
你将变成危险人物
You're gonna become a very dangerous person.
-喂  -米克  你好吗?
-Yo, Mickey.  -Hey! How are ya?
洛奇  我向你介绍这里的洗伤人 艾尔·西凡尼
Oh, Rock. I want you to meet our cutman here, Al Salvani.
-看看他的眼睛 -艾尔  你好
-Take a look at his eye. -How're you doin'?
-对了  -不算太坏  我见过更坏的
-That's right.  -It ain't bad. I seen worse.
你也不坏
You ain't so bad yourself.
-盖着它  很快没事  -你帮我盖着
-Cover up. Things'll be okay. -Cover up? You cover up.
去冲凉吧
Go and take a shower, will ya?
好  米克  明天见
Okay, Mick. I'll see ya tomorrow.
韦特摩那场是你做助手的?
You covered that Whitmar fight, didn't you?
所以他赢了
That's why you wanted me.
他是冠军材料!  我们有机会赢的!
Listen,we got a winner here!We got a chance!
他拳拳到肉  无人能及
He goes to the body like nobody you've ever seen.
你准备吧  我们会赢的
You just stand by, boy. We're gonna win.
洛奇  我跟你谈几句可以吗?
Hey, Rock, It's okay I talk to ya?
跟我谈几句?
Okay you talk to me?
当然可以
Sure.
我想了几个用你名字赚钱的方法
I figured some angle to make some money off your name.
我的名字?
My name?
-怎样?  -广告  我在行
-How's that?  -Advertisin'. I know about that stuff.
你对广告有什么认识?
What do you know about advertisin'? Huh?
你用我的名字赚钱  随便你
Hey, you can make money off my name, make it, okay?
我去冲凉了
I'm gonna take a shower.
-帮我脱拳套好吗?  -好
-Wanna help me off with these?  -Sure.
Trying hard now
It's so hard now
你一定会打败他
You're gonna kill him!
Getting strong now
Won't be long now
Gonna fly now
Flying high now
Gonna fly
Fly...
意大利牡马争夺拳王宝座
意大利牡马
洛奇  你怎么来这里?
Rocky. What brings you here tonight?
休根斯先生  那海报搞错了
Mr. Jergens, the poster's wrong.
什么意思?
What do you mean?
我会穿白裤  有条红间
Well, I'm wearin' white pants with a red stripe.
这没关系吧?
It doesn't really matter, does it?
你会给我们一场精彩演出
I'm sure you're gonna give us a great show.
去休息一下吧
Try to get some rest, kid.
晚安
Good night.
我做不来
I can't do it.
什么?
What?
我不能打败他
I can't beat him.
阿波罗?
Apollo?
是
Yeah.
我去了那里  想来想去
I've been out there walkin' around, thinkin'.
我在骗谁?  我根本不是他那个级数
I mean, who am I kiddin'? I ain't even in the guy's league.
我们打算怎样?
What are we gonna do?
我不知道
I don't know.
你已经很努力
You worked so hard.
没关系  反正我以前都只是无名之辈
It don't matter, 'cause I was nobody before.
不要那样说
Don't say that.
不用安慰我  那是事实
Oh, come on, Adrian. It's true.
我是无名之辈
I was nobody.
但那也没关系
But it don't matter either, you know?
因为我在想
So, I was thinkin'...
我输了这场也无所谓
It really don't matter if I lose this fight.
他劈开了我的头也无所谓
It really don't matter if this guy opens my head, either.
我只想好好的打一场  坚持到最后
'Cause all I wanna do is go the distance.
跟奎迪比赛  从来没人能捱到最后
Nobody's ever gone the distance with Creed.
如果我能撑久一点
And if I can go that distance...
当钟声响起  而我还站着
see, if that bell rings and I'm still standin'...
那将会是我人生中第一次证明...
I'm gonna know for the first time in my life, you see...
我不是废柴
that I weren't just another bum from the neighborhood.
够点了  去吧
Time, kid. Let's go.
我在这里等你
I'll wait for you here.
不如我在这里等你  你出去打
Or how 'bout I wait here and you fight, huh?
你今天好漂亮
You're lookin' very great today...you know that?
我要去了  但你不要走太远
I gotta go now, but, uh, don't you leave town, huh?
祝我好运  我需要运气
Wish me luck. I'm gonna need it.
祝你好运
Good luck.
艾莉  你觉不觉得这件袍太大?
Say, Adrian, you don't think this robe is too baggy, huh?
祝你好运
Good luck.
不要走太远
Don't leave town.
让我介绍我的拍档  赖士图
I'd like to have you meet my colleague workin' the fight with me... Stu Hansen.
谢谢  比尔·鲍温
Thank you, Bill Baldwin.
今晚非常兴奋  因为洛奇·巴尔博亚...
The electricity is all over the place tonight as Rocky Balboa...
那是什么?
Hey, what the hell is that?
我训练你做拳手  不是广告板
I trained you to be a fighter, not a billboard.
-是帮朋友的  -你有什么好处?
-I'm doin' it for a friend. -What do you get out of it?
保利得到三千元  我得到这件袍
Paulie gets three grand, I get the robe.
真聪明
Shrewd.
今晚这场赛事  两位拳手的高下
The story about tonight's fight, their difference in style,
正如一本近期的体育杂志所形容
you can quote a recent sports magazine which said,
是"野人对骑士"
"Could be the caveman against the cavalier."
后面有起哄声
I noticed a buzzing in the background now, Bill.
可能是挑战者准备上擂台
Could be the challengers getting ready to get into the ring.
洛奇  看我的女伴  花了200元
Rocky! Look at my date. Cost me $200.
-是250元  -我要走了  要工作
-250.  -I gotta go. I gotta work.
-这件袍怎么样?  -大了点
-How's the robe?  -It's a little baggy.
这个1赔50的冷门拳手 演绎着灰姑娘的故事
A 50 to 1 underdog living a Cinderella story,
他体现了全球观众的梦想
and he's captured people's imaginations all over the world.
洛奇  我们爱你
We love you, Rocky!
-祝你好运  拳王  -谢谢你来
-Good luck, champ. -Hey, thanks for showin' up.
他的纪录是44场胜赛
And his record... 44 victories.
38场击倒  20场败赛
He's got 38 by knockout, and he's lost 20 fights.
我不禁想  他捱得住吗?
Which makes me wonder, can he stand it...
要有耐力和技术支持三回合
the stamina and the skill to last the three rounds?
根据赔率就绝不看好
Because Las Vegas odds say no.
洛奇·巴尔博亚  正在攀上擂台
Rocky Balboa climbing into the ring now.
"意大利牡马"
The Italian Stallion.
袍后面有冻肉标志
Some meat sign on the back of his robe there.
你看见是什么吗?  森乐冻肉公司...
Have you seen what that was? Shamrock Meats, Inc.
背后又开始起哄  简直是震耳欲聋
A lot of noise coming from the back. You could go deaf with that noise.
有大光灯照着
You have the spotlights.
那是世界重量级拳王 阿波罗·奎迪吗?
Is that the world heavyweight champion Apollo Creed?
他坐在船上
He's in a boat... riding in a boat.
他在扮乔治·华盛顿吗?
Is he supposed to be George Washington?
很明显是  他戴了假发
Obviously so. He's got the hat on, the whole thing. Look at that.
全副装束
It's been confirmed.
世界拳王  阿波罗·奎迪
The world champion Apollo Creed
模仿乔治华盛顿
is doing an imitation of George Washington.
-他在派钱  -我不相信
-He's throwing money.  -I don't believe it.
我们小时候读书  说乔治·华盛顿
Remember we were talking about George Washington throwing the dollar?
抛1元
Throwing the dollar.
那时候的1元值钱很多
'Course, if you threw a dollar in those days, it went a lot farther.
现在他脱去金假发
Oh, he's taking his...
脱了假发  摘了帽子
White wig came off, the hat came off.
我要你
I want you!
观众非常兴奋
And the crowd is loving every minute of it...look at that.
这位就是世界重量级拳王
Here is the world heavyweight champion.
阿波罗·奎迪  他为全球观众
Apollo Creed... for you around the world
装扮成我国之父乔治·华盛顿的模样
he was dressed as George Washington, the father of our country.
我要你
I want you!
真不敢相信  是山姆大叔
Oh! Look at that! Uncle Sam himself.
我要你
I want you!
我要你们全部人
All of you!
我要你们全部人  他这样说到
"All of you." he's saying.
他好像一面大国旗
He looks like a big flag.
我要你
I want you. You.
-他在对我说吗?  -他在对你说
-Is he talkin' to me?  -He's talkin' to you.
-他在对我说吗?  -让他说去吧
-Is he talkin' to me?  -Let him talk while he can talk.
我要那匹牡马
I want the Stallion!
他说"我要那匹牡马"
He says, "I want the Stallion. I want the Stallion."
外国观众或者不知道  一次大战时
In foreign countries, during WWI,
美国陆军和海军的征兵海报里
there was the picture of Uncle Sam with his finger pointed like that.
就是山姆大叔那样指着
A recruiting poster for our fellows in the service...the Army and the Navy.
说"我要你"  那正是他在模仿的
"I want you." That's what he's doing a take of.
他在大叫
There he is. That's it, Creed.
奎迪三回合内胜出
Creed in three.
他那套衣服要多少钱?
What do you think that outfit cost?
各位观众
Ladies and gentlemen...
你们好
Good evening.
祝大家新年快乐
A very happy New Year.
欢迎来到费城
Welcome to Philadelphia.
今晚名人汇聚
Well, everybody who's anybody is here tonight.
时间...
Time...
时间不容许我逐一介绍  今晚出席的
Time does not permit me to introduce the many luminaries of politics,
政界  演艺界和体育界的杰出人士
show business, and the sporting world who are with us tonight.
但我想有请  拳击界的不朽神话
But I would like to present one of the immortals of pugilism,
擂台内外都是冠军
a champion in and out of the ring,
属于费城的"火辣祖"  备受爱戴的费西亚先生
Philadelphia's own Smoking Joe, the beloved Mr. Joe Frazier!
你好吗?
How you doin'?
手下留情  好吗?
Don't hurt him, okay? Go light on him.
他的拳击生涯是那么光辉
he's been in his career as a fighter.
现在他正过去跟拳王说话
Now he's coming over to talk to the Champ.
-嘿  怎么样?  -嘿  祖
-Hey, how 'bout that? -Hey, Joe.
-你避了我很久了  -不  祖  你是下一个对手
-You've been ducking me long time. -No, Joe. You're next, Joe.
-明白吗?  -下一个到你
-I want you, you understand?  -You're next, Joe!
他们一定是好朋友
They must be friends.
祖·费西亚
Joe Frazier!
赛事很快便会开始
The fight is on the way. Settle down because it won't be long now.
现在...要介绍今晚的比赛
And now... for the main event.
挑战者
The challenger,
穿白裤  重190磅
white trunks, weighing 190 pounds,
费城的宠儿
Philadelphia's favorite son,
绰号"意大利牡马"  洛奇·巴尔博亚
The Italian Stallion, Rocky Balboa.
而在我右面
And on my right,
穿着红白蓝三色
wearing red, white and blue,
重210磅
weighing 210 pounds,
46场不败纪录
undefeated in 46 fights,
绰号"灾难大师"
the master of disaster,
无可争议的世界重量级拳王
the undisputed, heavyweight champion of the world
阿波罗·奎迪
Apollo Creed.
我要你  你  你
I want you and you. You. You.
你  傻佬  我要你
You, chump. I want you!
你们两人都在费城比过赛 应该知道规矩
You boys both fought in Philadelphia before, and you know the rules.
不可攻击腰部以下 记着不可用头撞
No low blows, watch your heads, no butting.
握手  出去比赛
Shake hands now and come out fightin'.
举高手  傻佬
Put your hands up there, chump.
-快来比赛  -来吧
-Come out fightin'. -Come on. Come on.
看来洛奇很小心
Rocky's takin' it carefully.
洛奇很冷静
He's just going over and being calm, it looks like from here.
要摘下帽子了
There goes the big hat.
我从未见过有拳手会在意发型
I've never seen a fighter that concerned about his hair.
第一回合钟声响了
And there's the bell for round one.
两个拳手步向擂台中央  看着对方
The fighters come into the center of the ring, looking at each other.
洛奇还在观察
Rocky just looking.
拳王奎迪  迅速发动左拳
The Champion gives one of the left-handed jabs right there.
拳王随心所欲地 拳击较慢的挑战者
The Champ's stinging, the slower challenger jabs at will.
洛奇用面部来挡拳
In fact, it just looks like Rocky's blocking the blows with his face.
拳王不是在最佳状态
The Champion doesn't look the best he's ever been,
但他正在进入状态
but he's really moving now.
拳王笑了
Well, the Champion is smiling now.
他在玩弄他
He's toying with this man.
尽量令入场观众值回票价
Trying to give the fans their money's worth.
很明显他远胜挑战者
He's very clearly outdoing the challenger right now.
我会打倒你的
I'll get you. Come on.
他令对手的拳那样落空
He's just trying to make this man make him...see! Make him miss like that.
拳王在嘲弄他
Oh, the Champ is just taunting him now.
奎迪在跳舞
He's dancing around.
难以置信
I don't believe it!
-拳王倒地了  -确实如此
-The Champ is down.  -Yes, he is!
奎迪倒地了  真想不到
Creed is down! What a surprise this is!
这是拳王首次被击倒地上
This is the first time the Champion has ever been knocked down.
六  七  八
Six... seven... eight.
他看来没有大碍  有点呆滞但没事
Appears to be all right. A little glassy-eyed, but okay.
打他肋骨 努力  洛奇  加油
Let's go to work right now, Rock! Come on!
洛奇再出场  他好像很笨拙
Now Rocky coming back out, and he's like a bull in a china closet.
他很努力
He really wants it.
拳王一出场
Boy, the Champion's coming back.
就想了结他
He's coming off the floor now, and he's trying...
左拳  右拳
A left, a right, another left, another right, combination!
都打到脸上  那才是我们认识的阿波罗
Into the face! And that's the Apollo we know.
拳王正在挑衅洛奇打他
Now he's taunting him.
He's taunting Rocky. "Come on, let's go."
左拳  再一拳
Left. There's another left.
再一个左拳
Another left.
洛奇反攻了
There!
洛奇把他逼到围绳上
Left and right. Rocky's got him on the rope!
分开
Okay, break.
我们没预见到这样的攻击
I tell you, there's no way we expected this kind of hitting from him.
绝对没有  但是凭着拳王的能力...
Oh, no way, but with the ability of the Champion...
阿波罗狂出左拳  他逼了他到围绳
Apollo unloading a left, really trying to get him up against the ropes.
他们引导他回台角  洛奇找不到方向
They're leading him over to his corner. Rocky can hardly find his way.
他现在坐下来了
He's sitting down now.
我说过了
I told ya! I told ya!
你鼻梁断了
Your nose is broke.
-看上去怎样?  -更好看了
-How's it look?  -Ah, it's an improvement.
不要再做无聊动作 要出拳和走位
I want you to quit chuckin' and jivin'. I want you to stick and move.
攻他肋骨  要他透不过气
Go for the ribs. Don't let that bastard breathe.
他很棒
The guy's great.
他不知道这是场表演  他以为是拳赛
He doesn't know it's a damn show. He thinks it's a damn fight.
搞定那废柴  我们便可回家
Finish this bum and let's go home.
继续攻胸腹位置  你表现得好好
Stay to the body. The body! You're doing great!
奎迪在第一回合被击倒 然后强势反攻
Creed got knocked down at the end of the first.
现在他努力进攻
He came back strong at the end of the first, but he's working hard.
清脆的左拳  再加个强劲的右钩拳
A smart left. Another left and a right.
来了  他把对手再次逼到角落...
And now coming into the corner again...
洛奇·巴尔博亚在捱打...
Oh, Balboa's taking a tremendous beating here...
你不懂打拳吗?
Oh, come on, man. Can't you fight?
不要再装模作样  给点东西观众
Stop clownin' around here and give these people something to see.
他说要继续
He says he wants him!
如果大家没有意识到这是一场战斗...那就让我告诉你
If you folks aren't aware... you're watching a battle...I tell you that.
洛奇·巴尔博亚尝试反攻
Balboa trying to fight back.
噢  他击中了拳王
Oh! He tagged the Champ with a tremendous hook!
拳王想脱身
The Champion is trying to get himself out of there,
但做不到
but he just can't do it.
拳王的头部和身躯 被对手的左右拳狂攻
He is being barraged with lefts and rights to the head, to the body.
洛奇·巴尔博亚在重击拳王头部
Balboa is smacking the Champion right on the kisser.
拳证停止了比赛  但他们还想继续
And the referee's... they're ready to keep going. Look at that!
-回到你的台角去  -拳王回到你的台角去
-Back to your corner.  -Put that chump back in his corner.
-来  奎迪  -洛奇还想继续
-Come on, Creed.  -Balboa doesn't want to quit. Hey.
这是一场恶战呢
This is gonna be a tough one.
现在他被击中了  一个左拳
Now he's got him. A left.
左右夹攻
A hard left and a right combination.
-比尔  是什么驱使他还撑着?  -我不知道
-What is keeping him up, Bill?  -I don't know.
他连手也无法抬起来挡拳
He can't even get his gloves up to protect himself.
得停下来了
He needs to stop, Bill.
伏下  不要起来
Down! Down! Stay down!
阿波罗已高举双手
Apollo dancing around with his arms in the air.
五  六
five... six...
七  八  九
seven... eight... nine...
阿波罗不能相信
Apollo can't believe it.
拳王的右肋骨中了对手的左拳
The Champion got a left to the ribs... his right rib.
这真是一场精彩的...
Oh, this has been a tremendous...
-拳王  行吗?  -我没事
-Okay, Champ?  -Yeah, I'm okay. I'm okay.
我可能断了肋骨
It hurts, though. He broke my rib.
我看不见了  得打开眼睛
I can't see nothin'. You gotta open my eye.
-割开它  -我不想这样做
-Cut me, Mick. -I don't wanna do it!
-动手吧  割开它  -好吧
-Go on, cut me. Cut me.  -Ok.
试割开它
Try it.
天啊
Oh, God.
你内出血  我要叫停比赛
You're bleeding inside, Champ. I'm gonna stop the fight, understand?
你不可以叫停
You ain't stoppin' nothin', man. You ain't stoppin' nothin'.
-你叫停比赛的话  我杀了你  -知道了
-You stop this fight, I'll kill ya. -All right.
-随便你  -我出场了
-Go if you wanna go.  -I'm goin'.
你得去  使出全身本领  打倒他
You gotta go. You gotta give it all. Give it all!
你要尽全力  你要打中他
You gotta get him. You gotta work on that body.
已到了第十五回合  也是最后回合
The crowd is on fire. The 15th and final round.
他们看上去就像在打仗
They look like they've been in a war... these two.
拳王打中了他
Oh, the Champion really tagged him!
阿波罗明显在保护他的右边肋骨
And Apollo clearly protecting his right side... his ribs.
重左拳和右拳
Hard left and right!
-看他口里喷出来的血  -他在吐血
-Look at the blood coming from his face. -Oh, he's spitting up blood now.
洛奇出了一个劲右拳
A tremendous right hand by Rocky.
加油  洛奇
Go for it! Go for it, Rock!
听听现场观众的欢呼声
Listen to this crowd!
再一拳击中肋骨  加一下左拳 一拳中下巴
Oh! Another to the rib. That left hand again right to the chin!
他把他逼到围绳
Oh! He's got him up against the ropes!
阿波罗拳王...
Apollo the Champ.
不会有复赛  不会有复赛
Ain't gonna be no rematch. Ain't gonna be no rematch.
我也不想复赛
Don't want one.
洛奇  你坚持到底  打了十五个回合 你觉得怎样?
Rocky, you went the 15 rounds. How do you feel?
不错
I feel all right.
你打完第十五回合时 脑里在想什么?
What were you thinking about when that buzzer sounded?
艾莉
Adrian!
什么?  艾莉!
What? Adrian!
洛奇
Rocky?
女士们  先生们  今晚...
Ladies and gentlemen, your attention, please...Tonight,
洛奇
Rocky?
Rocky!
我们有幸能见证
You've had the privilege of witnessing the greatest exhibition
擂台史上最杰出的拳赛耐力表现
of guts and stamina in the history of the ring.
艾莉
Adrian!
洛奇
Rocky!
各位观众
Ladies and gentlemen,
我们的判决出现分歧
we have a split decision.
艾莉
Adrian!
洛奇
Rocky!
...裁判判奎迪胜出
...for Creed.
-有复赛吗  -不会有复赛
-No plans out there for a rematch? -Ain't gonna be a rematch.
我还不知道
Oh, come on. I don't know yet, okay?
你听到了...
You heard him, ladies and...
他是我朋友  放手
That's my friend. Rocko!
-你整烂我夹克衫  -走吧
-Hey, you're breakin' the jacket. -Let's go, Buddy. Come on.
保利
Paulie?
-艾莉  -洛奇
-Adrian? Adrian! -Rocky!
-艾莉 你帽子呢?  -洛奇
-Adrian! Hey, where's your hat?  -Rocky!
我爱你
I love you.
-我爱你  -我爱你
-I love you!  -I love you.
我爱你
I love you.